<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brefe treatyse declaryng what and where the churche is, that it is knowen, and whereby it is tryed and knowen. Made by Iohn Churchson</title>
            <author>Churchson, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10406</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10406)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 192:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brefe treatyse declaryng what and where the churche is, that it is knowen, and whereby it is tryed and knowen. Made by Iohn Churchson</title>
                  <author>Churchson, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[152] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules churchyard, at the signe of the holy Ghost, by Ihon Cawod, Printer to the Kyng and Quenes Maiesties],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1556.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>John Churchson may be a pseudonym--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatyse of the churche.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A brefe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe declaryng what and where the churche is, that it is knowen, and whereby it is tryed and knowen.</p>
            <p>Made by Iohn Churchſon.</p>
            <q>Beati qui habitant in domo tua domine. <bibl>Pſal. lxxxiii.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Bleſſed be they O Lorde that dwell in thy houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1556.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:3"/>
            <head>¶ To the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aruayle not gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader, that I haue attempted to penne this briefe treatyſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, a matter of ſuche impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce as requyreth a man of muche more readynge, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and iudgemente. For I haue not made this enterprice of any preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of good zeale, good mynde and intent, truſtynge that my well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned attempt, ſhall miniſtre oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſome ſynguler clerke of notable name, calling to his pitiful remembraunce, the piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſlaughter of no ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of ſoules, thoroughe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious factions, and ſectes
<pb facs="tcp:10406:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> in this realme, to bear vp (like as Atlas heauen) in the ſteade of Me a pigmey, this weighty cauſe, to perfourme and perfyt the imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpryce, and that this my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred farthynge ſhal moue ſome notable man,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> bountifullye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with Goddes treaſure, to bryng out thereof both new and olde, to the aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this matter,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> ſo neceſſarye to the reſtitution, reparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and mayntenaunce of euangelicall concorde in Chriſten religion, as the ſonne, fire, and water in earth, is not the lyke: not dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng but that the trauayle wil be moſt thankfully taken. For no perſon (except a reprobate) is ſo affectionate to vntrueth, but that he wylbe at the leaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> indifferent betwene truth and vntruth, his owne ſaluation, and dampnation, eſpecially yf it be remembred that humayn prayſe, and paynted flatterye, mouynge to the defence of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth, be but vanities, &amp; ſhall not auayle before oure iuſte iudge, who wyll iudge, not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the face, nor accordynge to the fleſhe, but as is the trueth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> For as he deceyueth not, ſo is not he deceiued by any colour, countenaunce, hypocryſye, or faced allegations of ſcriptures agaynſt ſcripture,<note place="margin">Ieroni. to <hi>4.</hi> pagin. <hi>374.</hi>
               </note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the vocables, but in the ſence, vnderſtandynge, ſpirituall marowe, pyth, and kernyll conteined within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If we would remember that the ſeruauntes of God ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:10406:5"/> not be contentious, but meke, tractable, mylde to al perſons, readye to be taught the truth, which is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike church onlye, we woulde not ſeake in the worde of peace, concorde, and vnitye, for ſciſme, diuiſion, and diſcorde, agaynſt vnytye: but euery of vs woulde make the petition that the manne of God kynge Dauyd,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 26.</note> deſyrous to lyue in vnitye, made ſaying: One thinge I haue deſyred of our Lorde: and that alſo I wil requyre, which is, that I may dwell in the houſe of our lord, all the dayes of my lyfe. This houſe of oure Lorde, the houſe of vnytye, is the mylytaunte churche of Chriſte, agaynſte whome the lighte harneyſed ſouldiers, and foreprickers of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:5"/> Antechryſt hath often ſkirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to ſpoyle it, (yf it myghte be) of gods precious verities, that Antechryſt their generall at his owne perſonall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his hugle army, maye haue the leſſe to doo, the more open way, and the frankar en tree to inuade our true meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hym ſelfe, who is the onely marke that his fore renners prickethe at, and he hym ſelfe woll ſhoate at. Wherefore god graunt to euerye factious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon repentaunce and turnyng of mynde to truth, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre to the vnitie of Chryſte, his catholyke churche, that he maye be in the ſafe protection of the inuincible hede &amp; capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thereof Chryſte Ieſus. Wherevnto Godes owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt
<pb facs="tcp:10406:6"/> our vertuous, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Soueraygne Lady the Queene, caſtynge her highnes pitefull eyes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our late moſt miſerable ſtate, hath by the godly aſſyſtence of our godlye and Prudente Soueraygne Lorde the kyng reſtored this her Maieſties Realme, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng ryght well ſuche to be no leſſe then infidelles,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicans, by chryſtes doctryne, whyche doo not humble them ſelfes to the ſame, for that (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Auſten) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſoule is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall body of man:<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>10</hi> ſerm, <hi>186</hi>
               </note> that is the holy Ghoſt, in the miſtycal body of Chryſt: and that doth the holye Ghoſte in the whole Church, that the Church doth in al her members of one body, and as yf a corporall membre
<pb facs="tcp:10406:6"/> fortune to be cut of from mans Body, the ſoule and lyfe folow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth it not: but whereas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber lyued beynge in the body, and deuyded, loſethe lyfe: ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blablye a chryſtyan man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke, whyles he lyueth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye of Chryſt the catholyke churche: but beyng cutte of, he is become an heretyke, for the ſpyryte of GOD, folowethe not a deuyded member.</p>
            <p>If therefore you wyll lyue of the Holy Ghoſt, kepe charytie, loue truth, deſyre vnytye, that you may atteyne to eternytye. Thus thys fynyſhynge wyth Saynte Auſtens wordes, I commende you to the handes of oure GOD of peace, enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly euen from the pryuye cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:10406:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:8"/> of my harte deſyryng you to reade thys lyttle boke with indifferent eyes, and deſyre of chriſtian concord, &amp; ſo I wyſhe you dayly encreaſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vertue and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg with moſt har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty farewel in our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:8"/>
            <head>the Churche</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuche as of late tyme, manye dyuerſe ſciſmes, ſectes, and hereſies haue ſprong vp in the churche of our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt, where with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame onely churche hath bene moſt contentiouſly diſquieted, moſt cruelly inuaded, and as it wer moſt piteouſly rented, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, to the extreame perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and diſtruction of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſoules, boughte, not with corruptible gold and ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but with the mooſte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of the immaculate lambe our ſauiour chriſt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye in this realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. I thought it ryght neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye to declare vnto you with no leſſe breuitie, than the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:10406:9"/> wyl ſuffer wherevnto you maye, and ſhoulde conſtantly cleaue, for the ſure vpholdyng and continuall maintenaunce of your true fayth agaynſt the fradulent thruſtyng fourthe of ſciſmaticall and erronious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. That ye ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parmane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t word of god &amp; the catholike churche,<note place="margin">1. Tim 3</note> which is the houſe of god, the piller &amp; fyrme foundation of truethe: as writeth the apoſtle Paule. The churche I adde vnto the wrytten worde of GOD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſayde worde for hys profundite, &amp; bountifull ſence is not to be expounded by the priuate interpretation of thys or that priuate brayne,<note place="margin">1. Pet, 1.</note> but by the vniuerſall interpretation of the vniuerſall churche, inſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:10406:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> with the holy goſt, bicauſe it is moſt playne the churche, to be the faythfull keper of the ſcryptures,<note place="margin">1. Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 3.</note> concredited and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted vnto her cuſtodye, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo, that Chryſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 29 Ioh. 14.16.</note> who is trueth, promiſed him ſelfe and his ſpirite of trueth to be reſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt, and reſident in the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke churche, to teach it all the trueth, not for a day, a moneth, a yeare or two, but perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and continually euen to the worldes ende, and therefore onelye mete, to whome the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of goddes worde ſhoulde be committed, and to whoſe onely iudgements and determinations in all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyes of religion, we ſhoulde faſtly ſtand: wherefore to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that you may the better know
<pb facs="tcp:10406:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſayde churche, I wyll god wyllyng attempte to open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you accordyng to the propor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of my gyft, what the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is, wher it is, that it is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and how you may know it, that you maye the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynely kepe your ſelfes ſound in the found fayth therof. For our aduerſaryes denying not but confeſſyng to be a churche, I wyll not ſpend tyme in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng it to be, but in declaryng the aforeſayde poyntes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to my promyſe. For the performance whereof, Fyrſte you muſt vnderſtand that the militant church of chryſt edy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed at the fulnes of tyme,<note place="margin">What y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is</note> war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng and fyghting againſt hell gates,<note place="margin">Gal. 4. Mat. 16.</note> ſciſme and hereſye, and hauyng ſouldyers valyante &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10406:10"/> faint, ſtable and inſtable, good and bad is a communyon, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietye and felowſhyppe called by god from Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tylitie and Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daiſme, to the profeſſion of one faythe, one Doctrine,<note place="margin">1. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and one kynd of Sacramentes &amp; from darkenes to hys marueylous lyghte: and by the ſame viſible Sacraments brought into the vnitie of one viſible body, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing one fourme of chryſtian religion. It is a congregation called, as wel appeareth by the greke word <hi>eccleliae</hi> deduced, of the greke verbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſygnyfyeth to cal out. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by Paule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vocati est sinunum corpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collo. 3.</note> you are called into one body. Agayne. <hi>Fiaelis est deus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>perque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cati estis in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietatem filij eius ieſu Christi Domini
<pb facs="tcp:10406:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> nostri.</hi> God is true by whome you are called into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſocietie of his ſonne Ieſu Chryſte oure Lorde, ſo that the churche is a conuocation, a congregatyon and ſocietie called by god out from the dampnable bondage of Sathan, vnto the lyuely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and free company of our lyuely head Ieſus Chryſt, from darke and blynde igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, vnto the merueylous lyghte and knowledge of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyan verytye. And the ſame called ſocietie and congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is knit together (as is ſaid) into one body, not in one place, but in one fourme and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one fayth, and one Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and that by one maner of ſenſyble Sacramentes, as is manyfeſt by Saynt Auguſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:10406:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>In nullum nomen religionis, ſeu verum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>6.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fau li. <hi>19</hi> c <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſeu falſum coagula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i homines poſſunt, niſi alique ſignaculorum vel ſacramentorum niſibilium conſortio colligentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men cannot be gathered into ani name other falſe, other true of religion, excepte they be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ioyned togyther by the communion and participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of viſible ſignes, or ſacraments out of the whych communyon and ſocietie, are heretykes, ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, paynymes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicates, heretikes, and ſcyſmatykes be not of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, by cauſe theye of theyr owne mynde went oute and voluntarylye forſoke the ſayde congregation, hauyng it in contempte, and contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perſecutyng it, nor pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymes, be of that ſocietie, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> they nother be, nor at ani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme were in the churche, nor do acknowledge it, no nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicates, bicauſe they by the publyke ſentence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, are ſeparate, excluded and put out from the exteriour ſoci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etie of the churche, vnto theyr repentaunce and amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyfe, but thoughe other chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians fallynge into deadelye ſinne, be not ioined to the good with the vnitie of the liuely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte, and bande of charitie, but doo loſe the grace of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall communion, neuertheles they are vnited to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good with a certayne exterior vnion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viſible ſacramentes (ſoo longe as they kepe peace wyth the Doctryne and profeſſyon of fayth) as was Peter the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his thryſe deniall of chryſt, as Iudas not withſtandyng his auarice, as ſuch whoſe doctryne our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Chryſt commaunded to be obſerued, notwythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge theyr euil doynges, and as are miniſters alſo perſyſtynge in theyr ſeuerall vocations, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by ſome ſynne mortall they be internally deuided. For as the dryed hand of the man, mencyoned in the Goſpel was before the healynge thereof, a membre of hys body, and as a membre, whoſe bones vaynes and ſynewes be broken &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth outwardly by the ſkynne continueth ſtyll a membre and a parte of the bodye, euen ſoo a chriſtian dyuyded inwardelye by ſynne, but cleauynge to the
<pb facs="tcp:10406:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> body of Chryſte the church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, by the outwarde vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the profeſſian and vyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fourme of one faith, and by the exterior participation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyſyble ſacramentes, the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſyghnes,<note place="margin">1. Tim 3</note> and fourmes of petye is externally ſtyl a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chryſt his miſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye the churche, although not profitable and continuethe in the externall ſocietye of the ſame church. For the militante churche conteyneth good and bad, penitent ſynners, iuſt and vniuſte, as is euydente by the parable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging forth good fead &amp; cockle &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue church, wherin was good penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; falſe couetous Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, &amp; yet of this church milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in an ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycle of oure faythe as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb facs="tcp:10406:13"/> 
               <hi>Credo ſanctam eccleſiam catholicam</hi> I beleue the holye called vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall churche, congregation &amp; multitude. Obſerue here by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way that this article namethe the church holye, not bycauſe it conſyſteth of onely iuſt ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and perfect chryſtians, for therein be good and bad, iuſte and iniuſte,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> conſtante and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtante, as is aforeſayde as playnelye teacheth alſo the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the nette, compriſynge good fyſhes and badde, and as playne is, by the greate houſe, ſygnifyeng the greate vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall churche,<note place="margin">2. Tim 2</note> which conteineth veſſelles, to honour and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and by dyueres other lyke ſcryptures, but it is named ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, bycauſe al chryſtians which make one church and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:14"/> be called of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly god by hys holy worde, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holye lyfe, be ſanctifyed and made holye by one holye fayth, and one holye Baptyſme, and do perſyſte in the communion of the ſame, for Paule wryteth to the Corinthian, churche a membre of the vniuerſall chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> notwithſtandynge that therein was the inceſtuous for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicator: contentious perſones, and doutyng in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the bodyes, as foloweth, Paule the Apoſtle by the voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus chryſte,<note place="margin">1. Cor 15</note> and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> Soſtenes a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten brother, vnto the churche, of God, whyche is at Corynth, ſanctifyed by Chryſt Ieſu, and called to holynes and holy thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Wherefore we maye not
<pb facs="tcp:10406:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> thynke ſtraunge, that the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche, whereof ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Chryſt our ſanctyfycation,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5</note> is the vndouted hed, conſeruer &amp; preſeruer (as writeth Paule) is named the churche of God, and holy, though euell chryſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans therein be commyxt with the good, for that notwythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge they be all called by one name, as affirmeth, S. Auſten <hi>In una domo omnes ſub vno ſunt nomine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſ. <hi>203.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quam uis enim moribus diuerſi ſunt, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tamen nomine cenſentur et profeſſione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In one houſe, all be vnder one name, for albeit they be diuers in maners, yet they be named by one name, and one profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſame affirmeth Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe mayſter to Auſten. <hi>In uno domo, omnes ſub uno ſunt nomine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſi.</hi> 2. <hi>timo.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>uno enim domini ſui nomine cenſent ur omnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In one houſe ſayeth S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:15"/> all be vnder one name, for all are called by theyr Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des name. Which is not diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from the principle. Eueri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynge is to be named by the beſt and worthyeſt parte. But our Lorde, holynes it ſelfe, is the beſt parte, and worthyeſte membre of the churche, beyng heade thereof. Therefore the churche ryghtly is called holy, of holy Chriſt oure Lorde and heade: yea, and of the holy goſt reſydent therein.</p>
            <p>Nowe that I haue briefly opened by the waye, the cauſe why the catholyke churche is called holy, ye muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſayde article, to teache vs the holye churche, to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of ſaynctes,<note place="margin">Vincent. Airen.</note> that is to ſaye: of Catholykes, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:10406:15"/> we are taughte the catholyke churche to be a communitie, ſocietie, or felowſhyppe of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholykes, becauſe they perſyſte in the communion of the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke and vniuerſall holy fayth, that was, and is obſerued in the catholyke, and vnyuerſall churche, and in the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo of the holye ſacramentes, whereby it is incorporate to oure holy heade Ieſus Chriſt, and clenſed in his holy bloude,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> hallowed with his holy ſpyrit, hath and doth holy thynges, &amp; teacheth holye and holeſome doctryne. Of this conuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, communion, and feloweſhyp, ſpeakethe the electe veſſell of Chryſt, Saynt Paule. <hi>Multi unu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corpus ſumus in Chriſto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> We beynge manye, are one body in Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:10406:16"/> So that the whole many, and vniuerſall multitude, profeſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g one holye fayth and doctryne, and being partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame holye Sacramentes, are the myſtycall body of Chryſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the Catholyke churche. Therfore S. Ambroſe ſayeth: <hi>Corpus Christi non unus aut duo christiani ſed omnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. in <hi>1.</hi> cor <hi>6</hi>
               </note> The bodye of Chryſte is not one or two Chriſtians, but all Chryſtians. As in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural bodye, one, two, or three, members make not the whole naturall bodye, but all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ioyntlye in theyr places: ſo the myſtical bodye of Chriſt whiche is the Churche, is not conſtituted by one or two chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but by all the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in theyr vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (whereſoeuer they be) ioyned and lynked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:10406:16"/> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> communion, and participation of the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. The lyke doctrine alſo S. Paule taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, <hi>Vnum Corpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> You are one bodye. Wherevpon Eraſmus dyd wryte as foloweth. <hi>Vnum corpus estis omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ab uno pendetis capite.</hi> You are all one bodye, and do depende of one heade. Thus it is manyfeſte, all Chriſtians to be the bodye of Chriſte, &amp; that the integritie of Chriſt, his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall bodye, conſyſtethe by no leſſe, then all Chriſtians, and that therof is one head, Chriſt hymſelfe, of whome the ſayde bodye, the Catholyke churche dependeth. Albeit that in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge the churche to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body, Chriſt is named the heade thereof, for elles it could
<pb facs="tcp:10406:17"/> not be his bodye: yet you may reade many Scryptures, that he is by expreſſe words named the heade thereof, whereof I wil reherſe this one folowing. <hi>Et ipſum dedit caput ſupra omnem eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> 
               <hi>que eſt corpus ipſius.</hi> And GOD the fathermade him (meaning Chriſt) heade ouer all the vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall churche, whiche is his bodye. Hereby you maye euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlye ſe, Chriſt to be head to all the churche, &amp; all the church to be his bodye, and by that worde all, Paule teacheth the churche to be a vniuerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Lykewyſe to the Corynthians, and to al chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans profeſſynge Chriſt, as the Corynthes dyd, Paule dydde wryte:<note place="margin">1. Cor 12</note> 
               <hi>Vos autem estis corpus Christi.</hi> You be the bodye of Chryſte.
<pb facs="tcp:10406:17"/> Wherevpon Primaſius ſaieth <hi>Omnes corpus</hi> al be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of chriſt for the vniuerſall and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of Chryſte was and is of all faythfulles,<note place="margin">Prima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us.</note> and not of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthe onely.<note place="margin">Chriſ. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>23.</hi> in. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Therefore Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſayth. <hi>Vniuerſum corpus, non illa Corrinthiorum eſt ſolum ſed que vbilibet toto exta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> terrarum orbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vnyuerſall body of chryſt is not the Corinthian churche, onelye, but the churche that is euery wher, through the whole worlde, for the churche of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthe, was but a particuler churche, parte, or member of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vniuerſall church. To be ſhort Paule proueth the ſame by the ſymylytude of a naturall body,<note place="margin">1. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſaying. <hi>Sicut enim cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us unum est et membrahabet multa omnia autem mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra corporis cum ſint multa, vnum tamen corpus ſunt. ita et chriſtus.</hi> For as a
<pb facs="tcp:10406:18"/> a naturall body is one, &amp; hathe many members, but thoughe all the members of that one bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy be many, yet they are but on body, euen ſo is chryſte, that is to ſay, euen ſo is chriſt, his chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as Chriſoſtome, Iherome, Primaſius, Theophilact with other olde aunciente wryters, do expounde it, as the bodye &amp; hed in man maketh one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in lykewiſe the whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and flocke of faythfulles, and chryſte the heade of them, make on churche.<note place="margin">Chriſoſ. ibidem.</note> And for that cauſe Chryſoſtome affyrmeth, chryſt in the ſayd ſcrypture, to be put for the churche, naming the churche by the worthyeſte and beſt part thereof. And S. Auſten ſayeth.<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>9.</hi> ho. <hi>17.</hi> trac. <hi>108</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vnus eſt christus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putet corpus.</hi> The hed and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:10406:18"/> is one chryſt. Wherefore the bodye, whyche is the churche, maye well be named by chriſt. As breade alſo is made of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable graynes, ſo the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body of Chryſt the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che conſyſteth of innumerable faythfull members, howe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be locally diſtant, for <hi>Vnus panis et unum corpus multiſumus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10</note> We beynge manye (ſayeth the Apoſtle, Paule) are one breade and one bodye, that is to ſaye, we beyng manye (lyke as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye graynes make one breade) do make one body, by on bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time and one faith incorporate to one heade our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt. By a folde alſo of ſhepe, is ſygnified the catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che: as is wrytten in the tenth of Iohn,<note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> and by Ciryll vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:19"/> ſame ſo that the catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is called alſo by ſcrypture. the foelde or flocke, paſturynge &amp; feadynge through the whole greate felde the worlde,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the catholyke churche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Ieſus Chriſt is the hed ſheperd. Nowe that I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petently declared what the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke churche is, my promiſe byndethe me to enterpryſe the declaration wher the ſame is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is</note>By thys worde catholyke, whych is to ſay vniuerſall, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the whole Churche, moſt manyfeſtly we be taught where Chryſte his Churche is, for it declareth the ſayde chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to ſtrecth out her brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches and members in to all and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry part of the vniuerſal world, as well affyrmethe, famouſe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:19"/> Auſten.<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>7.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. epi. pet. de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſie. c. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Questio certe inter nos verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ubi ſit eccleſia, utrum apud nos an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud illos, quae utique una eſt, quam maiores noſtri catholica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nominarunt, ut ex ipſo no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine ostenderent quia per totum eſt, ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum totum enim catholon grece dicitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A queſtion is amonge vs, wher the church is, whether it be among vs, or amonge them (meanyng the donatyſtes) the whych churche truely is one, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych our forefathers named catholyke, that they by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye name it ſelfe myghte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that it is through all, for thys worde Catholon, is in greke, expreſſed in and by all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole. This of Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, teacheth the holy church to be called ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke of the forefathers to ſ. Auſten,<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>2</hi> epi <hi>170</hi>
               </note> that by that very voca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, we myghte vnderſtande, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame not to be affyxed, or tyed
<pb facs="tcp:10406:20"/> to anye one Realme, nation or people, but to extend to al men of euery countrye, excludynge no man, that doth communy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate in chryſtes one fayth and one baptyſme, whiche agreeth to the holy kyng and prophete, Dauyd <hi>poſtula a me et dabo tibi gentes hereditate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuam, et poſseſsione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuam termi nos terre.</hi> Aſke of me (ſayeth the heauenlye father to his onelye ſonne our ſauiour Ieſus chriſt) and I wyl giue to the nations to thyne inheretaunce, and for thy poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the extreame bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the worlde, conſonant to Dauid is this of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Multi ab oriente et occidente ueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent et recumbent cum Abraham, Iſaac &amp; Iacob in regno celorum.</hi> Many ſhal come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, whyche ſhall reſte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:20"/> Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob, in the kyngedome of heauen, Euthimius<note place="margin">Euthimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> a greke author vp on thys texte, ſayeth. That by Eaſt and Weſt is ſignifyed all places of the vniuerſall worlde ſoo that of all the partes of the whole world there be, that do obeye the Goſpell taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles &amp; their ſucceſſours, whych hath, doth and ſhal wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes with mouthe or penne the catholyke faythe, vnto the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſſe people of the worlde, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to Chryſt,<note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> hys ſayinge vnto them, you ſhall wytneſſe me in Ieruſalem, in all Iurye, in all Samary, and ſo fourthe to the vttermoſte partes of the Earth. By thys Scryptures, it is moſt playne, the holy chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che to be catholike and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſall
<pb facs="tcp:10406:21"/> and not perticuler, as in England, or any other party<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer realme or countrye, and therefore the Apoſtles taught it and named it catholyke ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I beleue the holy catholike Churche, whyche is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon and felowſhype of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">Vincent. Lirinenſ.</note> that is to ſay of catholikes, as expounded it <hi>Vincentius Lirinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> aboue a leuen hundred yers paſt, bycauſe the church exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to all partes, vniuerſallye of the whole world. By Paule alſo it is euydent, that the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is vniuerſall, ſaying.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10</note>
               <hi>Non eſt distinctio iudci, et grecae,</hi> There is no difference betwene the I we and the gentle.<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> And by Petre. <hi>Non eſt perſonarum acceptor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſed in omni gente qui timet deum et operatur iuſtitiam acceptus est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lli.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:21"/>
            <p>God doth not partially accept men, nor is an affectionat eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of perſones, but he that fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth hym, and worketh rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, is accepted of hym in al and euery nation and place, ſo that no countrye,<note place="margin">Proſp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t cap. <hi>29</hi>
               </note> excludeth from God any perſon fearyng hym: for as Ioſeph made bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes throughout all Egypte, to laye therein their whete not moueable with euery wynde, euen ſo Chryſte our Lorde and gouernor, dyd conſecrate hys churche thoroughe the wholle worlde: therin to place his fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thefull, conſtant, and immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in all ſtormes of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, moued agaynſt the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryall poynte of chryſten relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bye the barnes, the churche is ſignifyed, bye all egypte,<note place="margin">Proſper.</note> all
<pb facs="tcp:10406:22"/> the worlde is repreſented ſayth proſperus, whereby it is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the holye churche to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholycke and vniuerſal, that is to ſaye, to ſtreatche into euerye realme regyon and natyon of this worlde. Wherewith that ſingular doctor. S. Auſten ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kethe moſt manyfeſtlye. <hi>Eccleſia est corpus Chriſti capitis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augu, in Pſal. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non iſta aut illa, ſed toto orbe diffuſa.</hi> The church is the body of Chryſt the hed ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, not this or that church, but the churche whiche is defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſpred abroade all the world. It is to be marked that the churche, whych is the miſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call body of Chryſt, is not a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler Churche, included in this or that corner, but a catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke congregation ſpreddyng abroade her beames, &amp; braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> into all nations, for thys purpoſe maketh fully alſo this notable ſaying of Saynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten folowynge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Credimus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m eccleſiam catholicam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au. to. <hi>10</hi> ſermo. de temp. <hi>181</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſciendum est quod eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am credere, non ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men in Eccleſiam credere debemus. Quia eccleſia non eſt deus, ſed domus dei est, catholicam dicit toto orbe diffuſam, quia diuerſorum hereticorum eccleſiae ideo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholice non dicuntur, quia perloca, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as quaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prouincias continentur, hec uero a ſolis or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad occaſum, fidei ſplendo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re diffunditur</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We beleue the holye catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, we ſhould learne the churche to be, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in the church, for the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is not God, but the houſe of God, catholyke he calleth it, becauſe it is ſpredde throughe al the worlde. For the conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of oure aduerſaunt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> are not for that called ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke, becauſe they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned within certeyne perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer places, and theyr owne ſeuerall prouynces, but thys churche ſtretcheth from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of the ſonne, to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge downe of the Sonne, with the ſplende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſhyning lyghte of one fayth. As bye the interpretation of this worde catholyke, ſ. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teacheth vs where the churche is, that is, the churche to be in all places of the worlde, euen frome the eaſt to the weſt, ſo he teacheth the vnleafull aſſemblyes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes to be but in anguler places, and ſeueral prouynces. Wherefore they be not the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche of Chriſte, but the malignaunte churche of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:23"/> Sathan. The places alſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Peter in the Actes, as Pontus, Galatia, Capadotia, Aſia, Bithinia, Phrigia, Pam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>philia, Meſopotamia, Egypt, the partes of Lybye. &amp;c. And Smurna, Pergamus, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, Thiatris, Philadelphie, Laodicea, the Epheſians, to whome S. Iohn dyd wryte the Apocalypſe, The Romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Corynthes, Galathians, Epheſians, Philippians, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locenſians, Theſſalonians, He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brues, to whom Paule dydde wryghte. The diſperſed tribes to whome Iames dyd wryte. The people dyſperſed as ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers at Pontus, Galathians, Capados, Aſie, Bythinie, vnto whom Peter dydde wryte, do teſtifye the church to be catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:24"/> and vnyuerſall, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally to extend into al real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, regions, nations, prouin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and countreyes, throughe the whole vniuerſall worlde, and therefore to be, not in this or that countreye onely, but to be in all the worlde, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt people of the four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes thereof.<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> For the ſounde of the Apoſtles, and preachers, went into al landes, and their wordes into the endes of the worlde. Therfore I may well conclude with Auſtens ſaying folowynge. <hi>Sicut per uerba dei noui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ubi ſit plantatus para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug, to <hi>7</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont. lite, petil. li. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er uer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba Christi, ubi ſit eccleſia, didicimus, per omnes, inquit gentes, incipiens ab Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> As by the wordes of God, we haue knowen where paradiſe was ſette,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.</note> ſo by the wordes of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt, we haue learned wher the Churche is: it is (ſayeth Chriſt) through al nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge at Ieruſalem. So that to perſons demaundinge where the churche is, the ſayd Auſten aunſwereth thus.<note place="margin">Aug. inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pist. Ioh. tract, <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inueni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus eccleſiam, in omnibus gentibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do fynde the churche in all peoples and nations. Agayne in the ſame place. <hi>Ecce habes eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam, per totum mundum.</hi> Loo, thou haſt the churche thoroughe all the whole world. To thys ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyl peraduenture obiect, that all nations, Iewes, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles beleueth not in Chryſte, nor worſhyppeth hym, but are infideles, and ſo inferre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che not to be euery where. To the which obiection,<note place="margin">Euthi. in pſa, 71</note> Euthimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and auncient greke doctour
<pb facs="tcp:10406:25"/> ſhall fyrſte make aunſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non dum tamen omnes adorauerunt, tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etſi ex omni gente ſit qui adoret et ſeruiet,</hi> Althoughe of al and euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and people there be, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doth pray vnto God, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp and ſerue God, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe al do not yet worſhip him. Thus this notable author af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmeth that although all doo not worſhyppe God yet to be ſome of euerye nation, whyche do worſhyppe and ſerue hym. With the ſame maketh Saint Auguſtine, ſayinge. <hi>Dilectio ex vniuerſo genere humano quod defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur toto orbe terrarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augu, in Io. tra <hi>67</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>facitet colligit populum nouum, corpus nouae nup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae filij dei vnigeniti ſponſae.</hi> Chryſtya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and gathereth a new peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple the body of the newe mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpouſe of the onely begotten ſonne of God, oute of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:25"/> whych is ſprede throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe the whole worlde, ſo that the newe people is not al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, but gathered oute of all mankynde. Thys confyrmeth Saynte Ihon in his reuelaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Apo. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Vidi turbam magnam quam dinumera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re nemo poterat, ex omnibus gentibus &amp; tribubus et populis et linguis, stantes ante thronum &amp; in conſpectu agni amieti sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis albis &amp; palme in manibus eorum</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dyd ſea a great multitude which no man coulde nomber, of al gentylles, tribes, peoples, and tounges ſtandynge before the throne and before the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be clothed with whyght roabes, and Palmes in theyr handes: here is to be noted, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gret multytude is the greate catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke churche, whiche is not al nations, trybes, &amp; peoples,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:26"/> but of all nations trybes, and peoples, ſo that of euery nation ſome there be, whych doo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſie and worſhyppe God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the mynde of the aforeſayde aucthorities, affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng the churche to be vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſal through al the whole world And Paule receiued the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhyp,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> that by fayth, Chryſte his name myght be obeyed in and amonge all nations, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignifyeng not all natyons, but that in all natyons &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes ſome wuld by fayth obei his name.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</note>Nowe that you know what and where the Churche is, ye ſhal vnderſtand, that the ſame churche is not inſenſyble inuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble and hydden, but ſenſyble viſible, manyfeſt, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> as playnelye teachethe the good and godly prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd ſaying.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>In ſole poſuit t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bernacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſuum.</hi> God hath ſette hys ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle in the ſonne,<note place="margin">Au. to. <hi>2.</hi> epiſ. <hi>166</hi>
               </note> whyche tabernacle as wyrteth Saint Auſten is the churche ſette in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne, that is to ſaye, manyfeſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knowen to all men vnto the furtheſt borders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. Lykewyſe in the canticles, the ſame Auſten maketh thys ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.<note place="margin">Augu. de cant. ca, <hi>5</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inſole poſu t tabernaculum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, hoc eſt, in manifeſto, poſuit eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> He hath ſet hys Churche in manyfeſt ſyght. With this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth Chryſte him ſelfe who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the Churche.<note place="margin">Croma i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non poteſt ciuit is abſcondi ſupra montem poſita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cytye whych is ſet vpon the hyll cannot be hydden this Cytye Saynte Auſten affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:27"/> to be the churche, whoſe wordes be theſe, <hi>Facile eſt tibi uide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ciuitatem ſuper montem constitutam de qua dominus ait in euangelio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>2</hi> epi <hi>170</hi> ad ſeuer.</note> 
               <hi>quod abſcon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>di non poſſit ipſa est enim eccleſia catholica.</hi> It is eaſy for the to ſee the citie ſet vpon the hyll of whom our Lorde ſpeaketh in the goſpell, that it cannot be hydden, for it is the catholyke churche. <hi>Hanc ignorare nulli licet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſti. Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>ideo ſecundum uerbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti abſcondi non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test.</hi> It is not lawfull for anye man to be ignoraunte of this catholyke Churche, therefore accordyng to the worde of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, it cannot be hydden, yf it were hydden, and vnknowen, it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to euery man, not to know it, and to be ignoraunt therof. Albeit that this be ſufficiente to ſatiſfye anye perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſible per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:27"/> yet you ſhall reade other mooſte playne ſayinges,<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>7.</hi> de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſ. c. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> of the ſame Auſten. <hi>Non est iſta eccleſia oper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta, quia non eſt ſub modio, ſed ſuper cande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labrum ut luceat omnibus qui in domo ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thys churche is not hydden nor ſecrete for it is not vnder a buſſhell or ſtryke, but vpon the candylſtycke, that it maye gyue lyght to all beynge in the houſe. Whereby it is manifeſt, that as a candele kyndled is ſet vpon the candelſticke,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble and to gyue light to al be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in the houſe. So the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the houſe of Chryſt, is ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and manifeſt to all, beyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, you haue therefore (ſaith Auſten) the church to be ſprede euerye where,<note place="margin">Aug, ibi.</note> and to encreaſe vntyll the harueſt, (whyche is the worldes end.) You haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> citie of the which he that made it ſayde. The Cytye cannot be hydden, that is ſet vpon a hyll. <hi>Ipſa eſt ergo quae non in aliqua parte terra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſti. Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> notiſſima eſt.</hi> That is therefore the Churche it ſelfe, whych is moſt euydently kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, not in any particuler parte onely of the world, but euerye where and in euerye place. Therefore Chryſte commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his faythfulles to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine vnto the churche vpon ſuche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after due admonyſhyon, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth irreformable, ſayinge. <hi>Dic eccleſie, ſi autem eccleſiam non audiet rit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18</note> 
               <hi>ſit tibi ſicut ethnicus &amp; publicanus.</hi> Tell the churche, but yf he will not heare the Churche, take hym for an ethnycke, and a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blycan, yf the church were not vyſyble and knowen, it hadde bene a vayne commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:10406:28"/> commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine to it. To take therfore vanitie from the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chryſt and to graunte trueth and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte to be therin, we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des confeſſe his catholicke chu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rch to be viſible, &amp; that it maye be as it weare fingre pointed as appearethe, bye. S. Auſten in this folowyng. <hi>Nunquid ſic oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demus eccleſiam fratres mei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augu, in Io. tract <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quomodo oste<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditur hominibus noua luna? no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne aperta eſt? nonne manifeſta? no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne obtinet omnes ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes?</hi> Shall not we (my brethren) ſhowe the churche, as the new mone is ſhewed to men? is not the churche euydente? is it not manyfeſt? rayneth it not in all nations? To the whyche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt church, he gaue manifeſt and viſible miniſters, as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Prophetes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> euangelyſtes paſtores and doctours, which
<pb facs="tcp:10406:29"/> are were and ſhalbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende vyſyble and not inui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible,<note place="margin">Math. 5</note> for to them Chriſt ſaid. <hi>Vos eſtis lux mundi</hi> You are the lyght of the world, which cold not be true, yf they were not ſene and perceiued. If the church be not ſenſible, but inſenſible, then the ſacramentes, the miniſterye &amp; eccleſiaſticall offyces, the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſyſtycall mynyſters, the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to Eccleſiaſticall offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Yea the worde of GOD wrytten and preached ſhoulde be inſenſyble, whyche ſhoulde be agaynſte Saynte Paule, ſaying.<note place="margin">Rom. 10</note> Faythe is by hearynge and hearynge by the worde of Chryſte. Seynge therefore by theſe aucthoryties, I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though brefelye: yet ſuffiſientli proued the catholycke churche
<pb facs="tcp:10406:29"/> which is eueri where, to be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſtly knowen, I will lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe god helping, proue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not to erre in the materyall points of our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: although ſome corrupte me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note place="margin">The ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche doth nor erre.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For albeit in this vnyuerſal churche, whyche is vyſyble, be many bad, ſo well as good, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt as iuſt, folyſhe vyrgyns,<note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> as wyſe, euel ſedes, as good ſedes and in the net badde fyſhes, as good,<note place="margin">Mat. 13</note> yet we may not thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame catholyke vyſyble Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, to erre in the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye poyntes of Chryſtyanitye: no more then dyd the apoſtles in ther belefe, preachinges, &amp; doctryne, bycauſe trayterous Iudas was of ther felowſhip, we maye no more brynge the
<pb facs="tcp:10406:30"/> doctryne, ordinaunces and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations ſet fourthe to vs by the vniuerſall Churche in doubte, by cauſe there be ſome bad therin, then we maye call in doubt the Apoſtles doctrine bycauſe euell Iudas was of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> congregation. If it be an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthe to affyrme that all the hole company of Aungelles in heauen, dyd erre, bycauſe ſome of them dyd erre and fell from heauen. Who wyll affyrme to be a truethe, the whole multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Chryſte hys Churche, whyche the ſcrypture calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome of heauen,<note place="margin">Mat. 13</note> to erre: bycauſe ſome euyll chryſtians therein do erre. The arche of Noe,<note place="margin">Gene. 7.</note> an expreſſed fygure of the Church: hauyng therin beaſtes clene &amp; vnclene hauing therin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Cham the wicked chyld of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:30"/> Noe, wyth the reſt that were good, erred not from the tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and protection of God, nor were drowned, in the deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng whaues of the ragynge floude, but was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually in the ſure certain and ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of almyghty God, &amp; ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued &amp; kept in moſt certeyne ſafetye, to the full ende of the ſaid floude, ſhal we then ſay or thynke, the catholyke churche, of chryſt, the verye veretye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by that arke, to erre and wander from Chryſt,<note place="margin">Ephe. 15.</note> and Chryſt his regiment, the hed thereof: ſeing that he is <hi>Seruator corporis ſui.</hi> The Sauyour and preſeruer of hys body whyche is the Church, as teacheth the Apoſtle Paule. Seyng Chriſt who is verytye, hathe ben, is,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:31"/> and wylbe contynuallye with hys church to the worlds end.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. and. 16.</note> Seyng (I ſaye) that the holye Ghoſt, the fyrme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forter hath ben, is, and wilbe without ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaſſe duryng this worlde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydent in the ſame, to teache it all the truethe, and therein to comforte confyrme and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhe it. At Antioch were cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne Iues, which taught the Chryſtians, that excepte they were circumciſed after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Moyſes, they could not be ſaued, after greate dyſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hadde therevpon wyth Paule,<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> and Barnabas, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues woulde not be ſatyſfyed (as ſectes commonly be not) in ſoo much that Paule and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, wyth others were ſente to the Apoſtles and ſenyors at
<pb facs="tcp:10406:31"/> Iheruſalem, for the deciſion of this queſtion, among the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, certayne that had bene of the phariſaycal ſecte, and then chriſtened, affyrmed that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought to be circumciſed and that the churche ſhoulde commaund the lawe Moyſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to be kepte, and yet Peter and Iames, with other the congregation there decreed to the contrarye, that the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhoulde not be cyrcumcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and were bolde to ſay and wryte. <hi>Viſum est ſpiritui ſancto &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis. &amp;c.</hi> It pleaſeth the Holye ghoſte and vs, to burden you with no more, but with theſe neceſſaryes. &amp;c. Althoughe in this councell and congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were ſome that erred, as they which had ben Phariſeis,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:32"/> yet we cannot without impie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie ſaye, that the whole holye aſſemblye dyd erre. Whyche truelye dydde ſaye: it pleaſeth the holye ghoſt and vs. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to affyrme the whole ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche of Chriſte to erre in matters of our fayeth, and neceſſarelye appurtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to chriſtian manners, becauſe ſome euell be amongeſt them, is a wycked ſclaunder to the miſtycall bodye of Chryſte, and an vngodlye blaſphemye to Chriſte hymſelfe, the heade thereof, yea, and to the holye ghoſte contynuallye reſydente therein, to whoſe inſpirations reuelations, inſtructions, and regiment, the catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che alwaye is obedyently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte, or els the holy goſt wuld
<pb facs="tcp:10406:32"/> not contynuallye abyde in it, accordynge to Chryſtes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe,<note place="margin">Pſ. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whyche promyſe cannot be vntrue, for he is faythfull in all his wordes. So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that euel be mixt with the good in the churche, yet we muſte not thynke it to erre in the wayghtye matters,<note place="margin">1. Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but to ſtande to it, as to the pyllar of trueth, and not to forſake it, as aduertyſeth vs Saynte Cypryan.<note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> epi 3 lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſi uidentur in eccleſia eſſe zizannia, non tamen impediri debet aut fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des aut charitas nostra, ne quoniam zizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia in eccleſia eſſe cernimus, ipſi de eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia recedamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although corrupt ſeeds do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and be ſene in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, Yet our fayth or charity ſhuld not be lette, moleſted, nor trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled, ſo that bycauſe we ſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte and noughty ſeades gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wynge
<pb facs="tcp:10406:33"/> in the Churche, therfore we ſhould relinquyſhe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the churche, but to ſuffer the euyll by charytie, beyng ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dious and carefull to kepe the vnytie of the ſpyryte, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of peace, as wylleth S. Paule and rather to be ſtronge in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leratyng the badde,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> then to be vngodly in forſaking the good But forſake not they the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che for corrupte ſeades, which for naughty chryſtians ſake do denye, refuſe and reiecte the Deciſions, determinations &amp; ordinaunces of the churche, &amp; her vnderſtandynges of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in ſlaunderynge the churche to erre in poyntes of our fayth and of chryſten rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon, bycauſe corrupted chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyans be amonge the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte.
<pb facs="tcp:10406:33"/> Let vs remember that no man hauynge the ryghte vſe of hys wyttes, wyll refuſe corne, bycauſe chaffe or cockle is myxt with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne, no more can he be eſtemed a ryght chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtyan, that reiectethe the vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall churche of Chryſte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baddes ſake therin. Foraſmuch as they whyche doo forſake the good holeſome and true Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of any preacher, for hys euyll lyfes ſake ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted obediente to thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of Chryſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia quecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicunt, ſeruate et facite, que autem faciunt, nolite facere:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerue kepe and do you all thynges,<note place="margin">Mat. 23</note> whatſoeuer they doo ſpeake and teache agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to truethe, but do you not
<pb facs="tcp:10406:34"/> thoſe thynges, whyche they worke diſſonant from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, then truelye he that refuſeth the felowſhyppe of the iuſt for the iniuſt ſake maye not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened an humble chyld to god our father, nor to the vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall churche our mother. As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great houſe wherin be veſſels not onely of golde,<note place="margin">1. Tim 2</note> and ſyluer, to honoure, but of woade and earth, alſo to dyſhonour, is not to be forſaken and refuſed for the veſſelles ſake of dyſſhonor therein. No more is the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Churche, whyche is the greate houſe nor her determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, to be contempned, for the euilles ſake therein permix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with the good, for in the churche the good and the bad,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:34"/> be to gyther as chaffe is with the corne ſayeth Auſten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mali et boni ſunt in eccleſia ſed apud here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos ſoli mali ſunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug to <hi>9</hi> in Io tr. <hi>6</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. nos fatemur in ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia catholicorum, et bonos et malos eſſe, ſed tanquam grana et paleas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good and euil be in the church but amonge heretykes be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye euyll &amp;c. We graunte in the Churche of catholykes to be good and bad, but as corne &amp; chaffe. Here is to be noted that by Auſten among the heretiks be none good, but in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of catholikes, to be not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly euell, but alſo good, yea and that lyke as corne &amp; chaffe, be together. For as good corne ſuffereth no detriment ne da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by myxture of the chaffe, but is rather conſerued &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued good therewyth, lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:35"/> the good people receiueth no corruption, contagion, nor infection in the ſubſtaunce of theyr religion, by the ſocietie of the euyll.</p>
            <p>But rather bye continual com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye, famyliaritye and ſyght of theyr fructles lyfe, do learne to deteſt and abhorre the ſame and do vſe there leuitie compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable to the lyghte moueable chaffe, to the eſtablyſhyng of theyre owne godlie grauytye, and the inconſtant, corrupte &amp; deformed errors of the iniuſte, to the tryall and confyrmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of their owne conſtante pure and ryghte doctryne. For as the wicked, euyll vſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good workes of the vertuous, ſo the vertuous, well vſethe the yll workes of the wycked, to theyr
<pb facs="tcp:10406:35"/> owne exercyſe and much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte, accordyng to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD hym ſelfe, who vſeth the euylles of the nough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the exercyſe, and profytte of the good and holy, that bye the peruerſytye of the euyll, the good maye profyte, be proued and tryed: as learne we maye alſo by Iob, &amp; Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whiche by tempting Sathan receiued no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage,<note place="margin">2. cor. 12.</note> but were proued &amp; tried to their muche good, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to thys of Paule. <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in infirmitate perficitur.</hi> Vertue by infyrmitye as temptatyon, perſecution and aduerſitie is made perfect, ſtronge, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vynſyble. And as good wheat being winnowed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wind fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaffe, is manyfeſt &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly appeareth good, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:36"/> good people, by the ſtormye temptation of the euyl, are tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good, and by the tryall are manyfeſtly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be good. Therefore Paule wryteth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Co. 11</note>
               <hi>Oportet hereſes eſſe, ut probati manifeſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiant,</hi> Sectes muſte nedes be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whyche be good maye be knowen amongeſt you, for by ſciſme, in doctrine, they are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to learne the trueth, and bi diuiſyon in lyuynge, they are excyted to ſeke vertue, and to be the more vygylant in Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, and circumſpecte in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, ſo that the good faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles, takethe no more detry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the companye of the badde, then dothe wheate bye chaffe, then golde by the touch of fyre, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pacience of Iob and Thoby, by the temptaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:10406:36"/> of Sathan,<note place="margin">2. cor. 12.</note> then Paule by the ſharpe afflyction, meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of Sathan, in his body, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles by the companye of traytorous Iudas. And for as much as Sodome had bene preſerued and ſaued from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction yf therein had bene but tenne good perſones,<note place="margin">Gen. 10.</note> why ſhoulde not we beleue the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke Churche of Chryſte, wherin be innumerable good to be preſerued, conſerued and ſaued holy pure, &amp; cleane from the deſtroying hereſies &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable errours. To be breife, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy father and learned Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Saynt Auſten wryteth as foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia dei inter multam palcam, multa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au. to. <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>110</hi> ad Ianua. cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>zizannia constituta, multa tolerat, et ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men que ſunt contra fidem, uel bonam ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam non app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bat, non tacet, nec facit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:37"/>
            <p>The churche of God ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and ſet among much chafe and much cockell, doth tolerat many thynges, and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it nother approuethe, nother concealethe, nother doth thoſe thynges, whych be agaynſt the faith, or good lyfe.</p>
            <p>Thus you maye vnderſtand, that the church in and among the chaffe, which ſignifieth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and fruteleſſe chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and cockle, ſignifying cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt chriſtians, ſuffereth mani thinges indifferent, infirmities fraylties and euels not maky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng agaynſt our faythe, nor con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tagious to chriſtian manners for vnyties ſake, as Chriſt dyd tolerate Iudas a theffe and a traitour, but the churche (ſaith Auſten) nothere dothe it ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:37"/> nother alloweth in the badde, no nor concealeth, nor yet win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth at any thyng in any wiſe repugnaunte to our faythe or chryſtya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyfe, eſpecially it doth not tolerate heretyckes, nor ſcyſmatykes, bycauſe theye be intollerable euyll, for ſcyſme, vyolation of peace, breache of vnitie, and ſeperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the inherytaunce of Chryſte, the churche ſpredde through al the whole worlde, and ſtretchyng into all ages, be intollerable. And no meruel, for the church is the kyngdome of heauen as teacheth the parable of the net and of the tenne vyrgynnes &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. 13. and, 25</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore it erreth not infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, nor doeth tolerate anye thynge that is infernall, for the kingdome of heauen is not the
<pb facs="tcp:10406:38"/> kyngdome of hell, of falſytye, ſcyſme, nor hereſye, leadyng to hell, but of verytye; concorde, and vnytye, bryngyng to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. No cauſe is therfore, why we ſhould cal the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole catholyke Churche, in doute, for no perſon vnfayned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, profeſſyng Chryſte, wyll af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme any one of the Apoſtles, whych were but members, of hys myſtycall bodye, the ſayde churche, to erre in his writing, ſhall then anye chryſtyan per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon holde the whole vniuerſall bodye of Chryſte, to erre in the greate matters, of our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Paule was but a chylde, of oure mother the Churche, and yet we are bound to beleue his Doctryne, to be true. For chriſt ſpake in hym, as he him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:38"/> wytneſſeth to the Corynthes, ſaying. <hi>An experimentum queritis eius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Co. 13</note> 
               <hi>qui in me loquitur Chriſtus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Do you ſeke experience of Chryſte him ſelfe, whych ſpeaketh in me? Shall not we then beleue the Doctryne of hys, and our holy mother the catholyke Church? ſpouſe moſte obedient to oure Sauyour Ieſus Chryſt, truth it ſelfe? in whom he hath, doth,<note place="margin">Au. to. <hi>9</hi> tract. <hi>89</hi>
               </note> and wyll ſpeake to the worlds ende, ſeynge he promyſed to be in,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note> and wyth her contynual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye no leſſe tyme. No man can but beleue it, excepte, any be ſo peruerſe, that wyll denye the Churche to be hys mother.</p>
            <p>To whom S. Cypryan ſaieth. <hi>Non potest habere deum patrem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cipri. de ſimpl. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui non habet eccleſiam matrem.</hi> He cannot haue GOD to be hys father,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:39"/> whych hath not the Churche, hys mother. Lyke wyſe in not beleuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church our mother, we do not beleue god our father &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently we do dege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre from all filiall nature, to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydgement, of our lyues, here in earth, and to the achiuing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g endles death in hel, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> humble obedience honour our ſayde holy mother the Catholyke Church, in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her preceptes, that we may be longe lyuyng, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beneth heare in Earthe, but attayne alſo to the longe lyfe, aboue in Heauen. Hytherto I haue declared the Church, not to erre, bycauſe ſome euyll per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, be therein, wherewyth, yf any be not ſatiſfied, but doth further affyrme, euery membre of the churche to be a lyer, and
<pb facs="tcp:10406:39"/> therefore doth infer the whole vnyuerſall churche, to lye, and erre. To them Saynt Auſten ſhall make aunſwere as folow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Deus per ſeipſum uerax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augu, in pist. Ioh. tract, <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tuper deum uerax, nam per te mendax.</hi> God is by hym ſelfe true, but thou art tru by GOD, for by thy ſelfe thou, art a lyer, ſo that although eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon of hym ſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſa. 115</note> and by his vityat nature, be a lyer, yet by the pertecipation of goddes grace and truthe in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, manye are true, as well appeared by the holye Patry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, Prophetes, and many others, before Chryſte, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and ſince that time, by the Apoſtles, Dyſcyples and holy Martyres, wytneſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the truthe wyth theyr bloude. For elles Dauyd hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:40"/> had lyed in ſayinge. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is a lier, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſte Paule, and other the Apoſtles had lyed in their preachynges, and erred in theyr wrytynges, the whych no chryſtyan harte can ſuffer to be affyrmed, but admyt, that the Deuyl is ſome time permitted to haue power on a ſynguler and pertyculer perſone in the Churche, yet it followeth not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath powre to ſeduce the vnyuerſal congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of chryſt, his vnyuerſal churche. For where Chryſt is, there cannot the Deuyl be, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderynge that no agreament is or can be,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6</note> betwene Chryſte and Belyall.</p>
            <p>But in the vnyuerſall catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke church is Chriſt, therefore is not therein the deuyl, Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:10406:40"/> is therein, for he promyſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayd catholyke churche, not onelye the ſpirite of truth, to teache it all the trueth, but promyſed hym ſelfe alſo verye verytye, therein to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally euen to the worldes ende. For that cauſe Paule calleth the church y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple &amp; houſe of god.<note place="margin">Apo. 20.</note> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apocalipſe moreouer it is wrytten, the deuyll to be tyed, and ſhutte vp in hell, that he nether myght, nor maye ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the peoples and nacions. Wherevpon S. Auſten wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his boke <hi>de ciuitate dei,</hi> theſe wordes,<note place="margin">Au, de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate dei li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ad hoc ligatus eſt diabolus in abiſſo, ut iam non ſeducat gentes, ex quibus conſtat eccleſia.</hi> Furthermore the deuyll was tyed and ſhutte vp in hell, that he myghte not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the peoples, of whom con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb facs="tcp:10406:41"/> the church. Here ye may learne of Auſten, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll hath not power to ſeduce the peoples and multitudes of faithfulles, of whom the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth. After it foloweth <hi>Nec enim dictum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug, ibi.</note> 
               <hi>ut non ſeduceret aliquem, ſed non ut ſeduce et iam gentes, in quibus eccleſiam procul dubio uoluit intelligi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not ſayde, that he ſhoulde ſeduce no manne, but that he ſhoulde not ſeduce nowe the peoples, in whom vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye he would to be vnderſtand the churche. Note here, that ſ. Auſten wryteth, that it was not ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the deuell ſhuld ſeduce no man, for ſo promyſed not Chryſt, but that he ſhoulde not ſeduce the peoples, that is to ſaye: the whole congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the church, to whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:10406:41"/> the ſpyrite of truth was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed to contynue for euer. Thus playne it is, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll maye deceyue and ſeduce ſome certayne perſones of the churche, and yet cannot ſeduce the whole multitude, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation therof. For ſo longe as an army ſtandeth together in aray, it is impregnable, and inuincible, but deuyded, diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and ſcattered abroade, it is mooſt eaſye to be vanquyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed. Lykewyſe Chryſtyans, ſingularlye, and priuately may ſometyme take an ouerthrowe of Sathan: but the mayne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, &amp; hoſt of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſal militaunte churche, hath ſo va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyanut, puyſſaunt, and experte a captayne in the myddes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, and that continually, that it
<pb facs="tcp:10406:42"/> cannot goo out of araye at any tyme, to take any notable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforte or ouerthrowe.<note place="margin">1. Co. 10</note> 
               <hi>Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim patietur uos, tentari ſupra id quod po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis, ſed faciet etiam cum tentatione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ut poſſitis ſuſtineri</hi> For he will not ſuffre you to be tempted, &amp; aſſauted aboue youre power, but ſo wyll do in the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you ſhalbe able to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine it, eſcape it, and to haue good ſucceſſe therin, ſo that he can and will kepe his promiſe, which was,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hel gates ſhould not preuayle agaynſt the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Whiche promyſe he made not, to the perticuler members thereof ſeuerallye, but to the whole churche vnyuerſallye. Therfore, although ſome ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glynge, waueryng, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge Chriſtians, do at any
<pb facs="tcp:10406:42"/> tyme erre, yet the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth at no time erre, in the weyghtye matters of Chriſtianitie. Yf the churche maye erre, then maye Chryſte and the holy ghoſt erre, which be reſyaunt therin, then is not the Churche buylded vpon an immoueable rocke, ſtone,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> and fundatyon, accordyng to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, then is not the Churche, the pyller and fyrme vpholder of trueth,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> then cannot the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſay truely, it pleaſeth the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye Ghoſte, and vs, then is not Chryſt the Sauyour and preſeruer of the Churche, hys body, whych to beleue were to muche vngodlye, but Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſayth. <hi>Homini ſi bellum inferas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15. Epheſ, 5 <hi>Chriſ, to.</hi> 2. <hi>ho.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>forte uinces aut forte uinceris, eccleſiam uincere nulla uis poterit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:43"/>
            <p>yf thou warre vpon a manne, perchaunce thou ſhalte ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, or be ouercommed, but no power forſe or ſtrength can ouercome the churche. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bye you maye wel vnderſtand that a perticuler perſone of the Churche maye be conquered, but not the whole catholycke churche <hi>Non de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit enim dominus ad tuendam eccleſiam ſuam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au. to. <hi>2.</hi> epiſ. <hi>169</hi>
               </note> For our lord wyll not be wantyng to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hys churche whych he bought and purchaſed wyth no leſſe, then wyth hys owne moſte precyous bloude, the infallyble euydence of hys deare loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde it, which will not ſuffer it vnarmed and withoute his defence. Vayne therefore be al ſcyſmatycall rebellyons conſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge againſt the ſame. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:10406:43"/> thys fynyſhed, I thinke it expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient to open to you the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyble tokens, whereby ye may know and infallyblye diſcerne the catholyke Churche, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> factious churche of ſcyſmatiks which tokens (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt others that I do ommit bycauſe oure aduerſaryes, moſte vntruelye do chaleng to be among them where in dede they nother are nor can be, but in the catholike churche) be theſe thre, vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie, antiquitie, and vnitie.</p>
            <p>¶ The fyrſte token whyche is vniuerſality,<note place="margin">Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie.</note> although I haue proued ſufficyentlye before, in declaryng where the Churche is, the whyche I praye you nowe in thys poynte alſo to haue in memorye, yet I wyll bryfely ſaye ſomethynge more
<pb facs="tcp:10406:44"/> for it. The ſcyſmatycall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, be but partyculer multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes in partyculer places, as the donatyſtes in Affryke, the huſſytes in beame, the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans in ſome certeyne prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Germany, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentaryes of late heare in Englande, wherfore it is moſt certaine, that our late particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler church, was not the church of Chryſt, whyche is catholike that is to ſaye, vnyuerſal tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughoute all the vnyuerſall world, as ye may perceyue by the promyſe of God, made to Abraham, whych is thys.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſemine tuo benedicentur omnes gentes.</hi> All natyons ſhalbe bleſſed in thy ſede,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> that is to ſai, in Chriſt as interpretethe it,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> S. Paule in hys Epyſtle to the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo that by God his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction through al nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſolis ortu vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad occaſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men domini</hi> From the ryſyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne to the goynge downe of the ſame,<note place="margin">Pſa. 112</note> the name of our lorde is prayſed and gloryfyed, as wytneſſeth the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd. Accordynge wherevnto Chryſt ſayde to hys Apoſtles. <hi>Et eritis mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i teſtes in Iheruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> 
               <hi>et in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Iudea et ſamaria et uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ultimum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> You ſhall wytnes me in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, in all Iurye Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and ſo in all places vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt partes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. Thus ye maye perceyue that our hed Ieſus Chryſt renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, nor newely builded his myſticall bodye the churche, to be included wythin any perty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer corner or part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world
<pb facs="tcp:10406:45"/> but to be vnyuerſall in Iheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in all Iury in Samarie and from thence in all realmes and countreyes euen to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme partes of the Earth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the auncyent prophecy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd good kynge and prophete Dauyd,<note place="margin">Pſa. 71.</note> whych is thys. <hi>Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur a mare uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad mare et aflumine, uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad terminos, orbis terrarum.</hi> (He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng Chryſt) ſhal rule from ſea to ſea, and from the ſea vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> extreame endes of the worlde, and therefore Saynte Ihon the Apoſtle ſayeth. <hi>Ipſe eſt propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atio pro peccatis noſtris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2 <hi>Aug. tra.</hi> 5, <hi>in epiſt Iohan.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>non pro noſtris tantum ſed pro peccatis totius mundi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(he meanynge Chryſte) is the propitiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our ſinnes, and not for our ſynnes onleye, but for all the ſynnes alſo, of all the whole world, that is to ſaye of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:45"/> all faithfulles dyſperſedde tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the world as vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dethe it S. Auſten. The ſame doctryne. S. Paul taught the Romaines <hi>Per quem accipimus gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam et apoſtolatum ad obediendum fidei in omnibus gentibus pro nomine eius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> Bye whom we haue receiued grace and thapoſtolicall embaſſye. That by fayth hys name may be obeyed, in all nations and countryes: by theſe and other greate nomber of ſcryptures, all and euery catholyke writer affyrmethe the Churche to be vniuerſall, and not nacyonall, not I ſaye affyxed to this or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nacyon. Whereof ye ſhall here that olde aucthor Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.<note place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia per vniuerſum orbem vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad fines terre ſeminata, et ab apoſtolis &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſcipulis eorum accepit eam fidem, quae eſt in vnum deum.</hi> The Churche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge
<pb facs="tcp:10406:46"/> ſowen and planted tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe out the vniuerſall world to the furthyeſt endes of the ſame, receyued of the Apoſtles and of theyr dyſciples, that fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whych is in one God. The ſelfe ſame ſaying hath Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius in hys fyrſt boke of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Tome, ſo that I ſhal not nede to rehearſe it, but nowe here that greate clerke Saint Auſten.<note place="margin">Aug. to. <hi>2.</hi> ad b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. ep. <hi>50</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia catholica ſola eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Chriſti, cuius ille caput et ſaluator cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſui, extra hoc corpus, neminem, uiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat ſpiritus ſanctus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vnyuerſall Churche, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye is the body of Chryſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of he is the hed and the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of hys body, out of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the holy Ghoſt gyueth lyfe, to no man. By this we are tau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght, corner &amp; partyculer chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:46"/> not to be the bodi of chriſt but the catholyke &amp; vnyuerſal Church onely, &amp; that out of the ſame, catholik &amp; vniuerſal chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, the holy Ghoſt gyueth lyfe to no man. Let vs therefore be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware of corner churches, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in is not the lyfe gyuing ſpirit, and earneſtly followe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle giuen by the ſame Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Augu. de agone Chriſtia. cap, <hi>29</hi>
               </note> whych is thys. <hi>Nec eos audiamus qui ſanctam eccleſiam quae vna catholica est, ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gant per orbem eſſe diffuſam.</hi> Let vs not here them, whych do deny the holye Churche, whych one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly is vnyuerſall, to extend tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole world, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is manyfeſt, that corner Churches, in thys or that nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dyſſentyng in relygyon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole not to be the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, nor of the church of chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:10406:47"/> for Chryſt ſayd not that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua or thys, or that countrye is the fielde,<note place="margin">Mat. 13</note> but ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſal world is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fylde, wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſede of god vniuerſalli is ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth and ſhall growe vntyl harueſt the worldes end, which if they dyd remembre, they wuld not ſaye that Geneua or thys or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> country onely hadde receyued gods worde, but that in euery countrye through all the vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall worlde, it is embraced, conſyderyng that by Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>In multitudine populi est dignitas regis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The honoure of a Kynge, is in the ample multytude of people, and contraryly in pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citye or fewe is the debilitie &amp; weakenes of a king, if we ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore wyll acknoledge our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kyng to be of honoure &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10406:47"/> puiſſaunce, we muſte confeſſe hym not to be a pertyculer or a nacionall king and hed of this or that nation onelye, but to reygne in euery countrye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole world,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> except we ſhoulde ſaye that Chryſte hath loſt hys inherytaunce the vnyuerſall churche, ſpred tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe the vnyuerſal worlde, and that he is dryuen to a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Germanye, to be but a dymye anguler kyng, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, whych were a playne blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemye, ſoo that, whatſoeuer multytude ſettythe fourthe a doctryne dyſſentyng from the vnyuerſall doctryne of the vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſal Churche, maye well be iudged, not to be of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Churche of Chryſt. Of the whych churche we be ſayeth. <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lirine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Si hanc fidem uera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10406:48"/> eſſe fateamur, quam tota per orbem terre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, confiretur eccleſia.</hi> Yf we confeſſe thys fayth to be true, whyche the whole Churche through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole worlde dothe confeſſe. Agayne. <hi>Si id teneamus, quod ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum est.</hi> Yf we holde &amp; kepe that, whiche is euerye where, and in euery country beleued. Some peraduenture wyll in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueye agaynſt this, ſayenge. The flocke of Chriſte is lytle,<note place="margin">Luk. 12. Math. 7.</note> and the way to lyfe is narow, therefore the churche cannot be large and greate. To that aunſwereth that holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed father S. Auſten in his epyſtle, <hi>ad Vincentium,</hi> agaynſt the Donatiſtes,<note place="margin">Augu. to 2 epi <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ipſa eſt de cuius pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate dicitur in comparatione multorum malorum. Quia augusta &amp; arcta uia est, que ducit aduitam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; pauel ſunt qui ambu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lant in illa. Et rurſus ipſa est, de cuius mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudine
<pb facs="tcp:10406:48"/> dicitur, ſic erit ſemen tuum, ſicut ſtelle celi, et ſicut haraena maris, ijdem quip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe fideles ſancti &amp; boni: et in comparatione plurimorum malorum, pauci, &amp; perſe ipſi multi ſunt, quia multi filij deſertae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 4.</note> 
               <hi>magis quam eius, quae habet uirum, &amp; multi ab o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riente &amp; occidente uenient &amp; recumbent cum Abraham Iſaac &amp; Iacob in regno coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Et exhibet ſibi deus populum habun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantem, emulatorem bonorum operum, &amp; multa milia, quae numerare nemo poterat, ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entur in Apocalipſi, ex omni tribu et lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua in ſtolis albis, palmiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> uictricibus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoca. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That is the churche, of whoſe fewnes it is ſpoken in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of manye euyll. For the ſtreight and narrowe way is, whiche leadeth vnto lyfe, and fewe there be whiche walcke in it: and contrarylye, that is the church, of whoſe multitude it is ſayde, ſo ſhall thy ſeede be as the ſtarres of the firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:49"/> and the ſande of the ſea, for the ſame faythfulles be holye and good, and in compariſon of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye euell, be fewe, and by them ſelues the ſame be manye: for the chyldren of her whyche is deſolate of a huſband, be more in noumbre, then the chyldren of her which hath a huſbande, and manye ſhal come from the Eaſt and from the Weſte, and ſhal reſt with Abraham Iſaac and Iacob, in the kyngedome of heauen, and God doth exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite vnto hym ſelfe an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of people, followers of good workes. And many thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſandes, whom no man can nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, be ſene in the apocalypſe, of all and euery trybe, &amp; tonge, in whyte robes, and victorius palmes. Here is to be noted,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:49"/> that S. Auſten affyrmeth the catholyke churche of Chriſt, to be of a fewe noumber, yf it be conferred with the euyll mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, whiche beynge compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the good, incomparably in number do excede. The pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grems and ſober paſſengers, thoroughe the narowe waye, are but a ſmall multitude, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge compared vnto the huge noumber, raungynge and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge thoroughe the breade wayes. Chriſte his redolente flocke of meke lambes, is but a lytle flocke, in comparyſon of the greate ſtynckynge hearde of the deuyls ſturdy rammiſhe goates, but yf the ſtreyght paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers thorough the narowe waye, and the lyttle flocke of Chryſt, be accompted by them
<pb facs="tcp:10406:50"/> ſelues, without collation, and compariſon to the euyll, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge thoroughe the broade waye, they be manye and innu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merable, lyke as be the ſterres in the fyrmament, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſande in the ſea, as mooſt manyfeſtly appeareth by the ſcriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue alleged of the ſayde Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and is truely called by the Prophete Dauyd <hi>Eccleſia magna,</hi> the greate church and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,<note place="margin">Pſa. 21.</note> becauſe it extendeth in to all the furtheſte partes, and borders of the worlde, and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conteineth many thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſandes whom no man can no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as is alledged oute of the Apocalypſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>Nowe to the ſecond token which is antiquitie or au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cietie wherby ye may deſcerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:10406:50"/> catholyke Church, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body, of our ſauyour Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus, from the late ſpronge vppe anguler Churches, Whereof Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the hed, for the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che whereof Chryſt is the hed, is of ſuche antiquitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he him ſelfe, whyche is. <hi>Antiquus dierum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dani. 7.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde auncyent, and which ſayd <hi>Antequam Abraham fieret, ego ſum.</hi> Before Abraham was made, or borne, I am, dyd founde it: and that before anye wrytten Scryptures, for Adam, Eue, Abell, Seath, Noe, Abraham, Lothe, wyth many other faith fulles, ware before Moyſes, a longe tyme, before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement, wrytten in ſtonye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and before Scryptures, wrytten in an outwarde ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce. And the ſame Church
<pb facs="tcp:10406:51"/> Chryſt beyng vyſyble heare in Earth, accordyng to hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> mentioned in Mathew, whych was, vpon this rocke, and fyrme foundation, I will buylde my Churche, dyd new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye edyfye, renewe and repaire out of hys owne ſyde, as wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Saynte Chryſoſtome, ſayeng.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſ, to. <hi>2.</hi> homil. ad Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitos <hi>26</hi> Ihero. to <hi>4.</hi> ſermo. de reſur. domini. Proſper. de promiſ et predic par. <hi>1.</hi> ca <hi>1</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ex latere ſuo Christus edificauit eccleſiam ſicut de latere Adam eius coniunx Eua pro lata est. Nam hac de cauſa Paulus quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> testatur dicens. De corpore eius et oſſibus eius ſumus, latus uidelicet illud ſignificans, nam ſicut de latere illo, Deus fecit femina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> procreari, ſic et de ſuo latere Chriſtus aqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis et ſanguinem dedit: unde repararetus eccleſia.</hi> Chryſt builded his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che oute of his owne ſyde, lyke as out of the ſide of Adam his wife Eue was brought fourth for Paule alſo wytneſſeth, for
<pb facs="tcp:10406:51"/> that cauſe ſaying, we be of his body and of hys bones, ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeng ſurely hys ſyde. For as God dyd procreat the woman oute of the ſame ſyde, euen ſoo Chryſte gaue out of hys owne ſide, water and bloude, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the church ſhould be repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and renewed, ſo that al the fyrſt orygynall beyng of chryſt his church, was not originally begone euen at the giuyng of water and bloude, oute of hys ſyde, but the newe buyldynge, reperation, and renewynge thereof, as ſayeth the Prophet Amos, &amp; Sainte Chriſoſtome,<note place="margin">Amos. 9 Acte. 16.</note> and the reedifyeng to a perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, accordyng to thys of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd. <hi>Deus uirtutum reſpice de celo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 79.</note> 
               <hi>et Vide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t uiſita uincam iſtam, et perfice cam quam plantauit dextera tua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loke downe o God of power
<pb facs="tcp:10406:52"/> from Heauen ſe and vyſyt this vyneyard and make it perfect whych thy ryght hande hathe planted, Thus the Prophette deſyred not the extirpation of godds olde vyneyard, and the plantynge of a newe, but deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the perfectynge of the olde, by hys myghty power, al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy planted. The whych vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde is the Churche, as affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Prophet Eſay.<note place="margin">Eſaye. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Vinea domini domus Iſraell.</hi> The vineyard of our Lorde is the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, and the Chryſtyans be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyrytuall Iſraelytes.</p>
            <p>Thys ſpyrytuall vyneyarde Chryſt hys churche, is newlye buylded and brought to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by propagation, dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and enlargynge the ſame out of Iurye in to all regyons and contreies, by connecting
<pb facs="tcp:10406:52"/> and coupplynge the Iues and Gentyles, the olde church and the newe together in one,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> him ſelfe being the hed corner ſtone by repayrynge and renewyng it with a more habundante ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte, wyth a more plentythe of grace, wyth open verytyes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a newe and perfect lawe, new and perfect ſacramentes, with newe prieſtehoode, and newe perfect ſacrifyſe, the olde imper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectes beynge abolyſhed. And ſo the churches old worne gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes the fygures put of, ſhe proceded not into a corner, but into all the worlde, not vnder a veyle couertelye, hyddenlye, and inuiſiblie, but manifeſtlie, openlye, and vyſiblye, adorned wyth a newe vyſyble habyte, &amp; tyre, as it were wyth a newe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:53"/> diſtynct ſhape from her ſelfe, in her olde forme before the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of tyme vnpoliſhed yea ſhe came fourth of Chryſt his ſide all perfect and newe in the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and bloude,<note place="margin">Galat. 4.</note> guyſhyng oute of hys ſayde ſyde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note>For Paule ſayth, that Chryſt gaue him ſelfe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death for his Church, to ſanctyfy it, clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing it, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lauacre of water by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of lyfe, &amp; dyd waſhe vs from our ſynne in hys bloude, as teacheth Saint Ihon.<note place="margin">Apoc. 1.</note> And as the Church was fyrſt was fyrſt buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before the wrytten ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of the olde Teſtamente, ſo was the ſame reedifyed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and renewed before the wrytten Scrypture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe Teſtament For Chryſte &amp; hys Apoſtles preached, before that
<pb facs="tcp:10406:53"/> any externall wrytyng or prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng was therof, as it is moſt playne to all men, exercyſed in readyng of Scrypture, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient learned writers. And yet no true chryſtyan woll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the doctryne of Chryſte, &amp; of hys Apoſtles then vnwryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be vntrue, but to be of no leſſe verytye vnwrytten, then after beyng wrytten. For it is not true, bycauſe it is wrytten, but bycauſe Chryſt (who is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie) ſpake &amp; taught it, which verytye vnwrytten aunciette to the veritie, after writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, toke not aucthoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verity, for then Chryſt beyng Mayſter, and his worde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrytten taught by mouth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, had taken aucthoritie of the worde after wrytten by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe
<pb facs="tcp:10406:54"/> and Ihon, but hys Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles and ſeruauntes, yea and of the writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word by Marke, &amp; Luke, but Dyſcyples to his Apoſtles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which notable inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenience to auoyde, we muſte rather affyrme the wrytten worde by the Dyſcyples and minyſters, to receue credence and eſtimatyon of the vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten worde taught by Chryſte hym ſelfe there mayſter. And that bicauſe the worde writen was, and is conformable and agreable by the teſtimonye of the church, to the auncient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrytten word, which the ſayd churche had receued of Chryſt truethe hym ſelfe. Soo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrytten truth came not after to brynge aucthoritie to the vnwrytten, but godlye to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhe,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:54"/> put in mynde, &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the chryſtian poſteritie, that the churche auncient to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrytten worde, had receyued the ſame of Chryſt hys mouth, and vſed it, before the outward wrytyng thereof, and that we ſhold beleue Ieſus to be Chriſt the very ſonne of god, and that ſo beleuynge we myghte haue lyfe eternall by hys name. Wherefore the antiquytye of of the Churche, is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, but moſte reuerentlye &amp; obedyently to be embraced, as teacheth that great clerke S. Baſyll.<note place="margin">Baſil. de ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanct.</note> 
               <hi>Veneranda ſunt uetuſta dogma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta, quod obantiquitatem, ceu canitiem qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, habeant quiddam reuerendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The auncient decres and ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunces, are to be reuerenced, bycauſe for their olde antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and as a man myght ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:55"/> for theyr hore auncietye, they haue certayne great reuerente matter in them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 6.</note>That notable wyſe manne Ieſus Sirache gaue this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement. <hi>Non te praetereat narratio ſeniorum. &amp;c</hi> Forget not the ſaiynges of the elders for they haue learned the truthe of there forefathers, &amp; of them thou ſhalte learne vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, and thou ſhalt learne to geue wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede is, a wiſe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            <p>Shall we then contrary to Goddes word leaue our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyettes, and elders, to followe the fonde ſayinges, of oure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and raſhe yonglyngs and yong phantaſtycall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, whych Ieſus Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rache,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.</note> maketh wyſe Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:55"/> in his prouerbs. <hi>Ne tranſgrediaris ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minos antiquos, quos poſueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t patres tui.</hi> Paſſe not out of the olde aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient borders, whych thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers hath appoynted. The borders and lymytes vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he dothe paſſe and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe as wryteth that holye &amp; learned clerke Alexandre the fyrſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexa.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ſtatuta patrum postponit at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> confundit.</hi> The whych regardeth not but omitteth confoundeth, and dyſordereth the determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our auncient fathers The ſcrypture commaundeth vs to be myndefull of olde aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent tyme paſte,<note place="margin">Deu. 32.</note> and to aſke our forefathers, &amp; they ſhould tel and teach vs, but now ſome endeuorynge to tourne ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſtly the rootes of trees vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, to ſette the carte before
<pb facs="tcp:10406:56"/> the horſes, to make all ryght or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre prepoſterous, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde all Chryſt hys ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and doctrine, do teach con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chryſt, to contempne antiquitye as dotage, and to aſke and beleaue the inuenile ſucceſſoures, bearinge men in hand, dampnable ignoraunce, to be in our holi learned aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, &amp; knowledge with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be in their after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng poſterytie, to thend that chyldren ſhuld contrary to the ſcrypture, ſette their fathers to ſcole. It is therefore verye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that by ſcrypture it ſelfe, we are premonyſhed, taughte and commaunded to be ware and cyrcumſpecte, that in no wyſe we vyolate the lawes, or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynaunces, and determynati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:10406:56"/> of oure holye forefathers, but wyth reuerente obedience to obeye and followe them, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe next vnto goddes holye worde, and hys catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, our moſt comfortable god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye and infallyble ſtaye, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth in them, perſiſtyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnytie of the Catholyke faith, and the ſame hath delyuered, vnto their ſucceſſours, as thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe it were with one penne wrytten. Yf therfore any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or doubte doo aryſe, wee muſt (ſayeth that olde wryter, <hi>Lirinenſis</hi>) haue recourſe to the ſayinges of our holye fathers,<note place="margin">Vin. Lir.</note> whych in their ſeuerall tymes, contynuynge in the vnytye of Chryſt hys churche, hath bene approued maiſter, and therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient learned father Leo,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:57"/> wryteth as foloweth.<note place="margin">Leo epiſt. ad Marti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anam Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gustum.</note> 
               <hi>Qui etiam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi principuis meritis optuno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iudicio, legi time fui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſet ac ſolemniter ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, contra reuerentiam tamen canonum paternorum, contra ſancti ſpiritus inſtituta, contra anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatis exempla, nullis poſſet ſuffragijs ad iuuari.</hi> Whoſoeuer althoughe he beyng of excellent meryte and of excellent iudgemente were leafully and ſolemnely ordred, yet doyng agaynſt the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t canons of our auncient fathers agaynſt the ordinaunces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt, agaynſt the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of antiquitye, he can by no ſuffragies, be holpen. Marke heare I praye you, that thys ſynguler clarke, of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryes, neuer reproued, affirmeth amongeſt other thynges, that agaynſt examples of antiquiti we can bi no ſuffrages nor prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:10406:57"/> be holpen. Wherfore in the name of our ſauyoure Ieſus Chryſt let vs bannyſhe and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yle all the prophane newe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes, accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde of Paule in Tymothe, who commaunded vs not to eſchew antiquities,<note place="margin">1. Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nor olde nor aunti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, but newe doctrynes, ſeing therfore newe doctrynes are to be auoyded, antyquyty is to be embraſed, and ſeynge by Paule that newe doctryne is prophane, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyquity muſt nedes be ſacred and holye, the whych ſacred antyquytye (ſaieth Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lyrynenſis) an olde aucthor we ſhall folowe <hi>Si ab his ſenſibus nullate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s recedamus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us.</note> 
               <hi>quos ſanctos maiores ac patres noſtros celebraſſe manifeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yf that we do by no meanes go backe from thoſe vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:58"/> &amp; iudgementes, whom it is playne our holy aunciet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and forefathers, to haue preached and publyſhed.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame antiquitie Saint Paule admonyſhed the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians ſaying: If any man appeare to be contentious, he muſt vnderſtand that we haue no ſuch cuſtome, nor the church of God, whereby it is mooſte playne, that the church of God in S. Paules tyme dyd much and highly eſteame cuſtomes, how much more then ſhoulde auncient cuſtomes, preſcrypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and traditions deryued, deduced &amp; brought from chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes primatyue Church, to the next age, and ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> age to age, contynuallye vntyll thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, be much eſtemed, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:10406:58"/> embraced, and reuerentlye obeied of vs in theſe latter daies wherein many arroganthedes are deſyrous of neuer receiued doctrines, procedyng of proud ſingularitie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our euer approued and r eceyued doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, religion, cuſtomes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions and traditions euen from the begynnyng.</p>
            <p>The whych Saint Iherome, hauing in muche remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſayd reuerentlye.<note place="margin">Ieron. ad Oceanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> et pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llam ſenex tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo fidem in qua puer natus ſum</hi> I being an olde man, wyl kepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fayth that I a chylde was borne in, knowyng ryght well not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnyuerſalytie, but alſo anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quytie of the vnyuerſall Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne and relygion to be a ſure and an vndouted token of the catholyke Churche, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:10406:59"/> he dyd wryght vnto The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ophilus. <hi>Scito nobis nihileſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> antiquius, quam nec Chriſti iura,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ihero. in Theophi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lum,</note> 
               <hi>nec patrum tranſire terminos,</hi> Knowe thou O Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phile, nothyng to be vnto vs, more acceptable, than not to tranſgreſſe &amp; paſſe the lawes, of Chryſt, and the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our forefathers.<note place="margin">Galat. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And no merueyle for Paule hym ſelffe called immedyatlye by Chriſt, and bountifully brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed wyth the Holye ghoſte, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to Iheruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know hys auncyettes and predyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoures the apoſtles,<note place="margin">Galat. 2.</note> and to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſulte wyth them, leſte he hadde renne in vayne, that is to ſaye, leſt he had not beleued as they beleued and had not preached,<note place="margin">Tertulli. contra Merchio nem. li. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> as they preached.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as Paule ſo nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:10406:59"/> Apoſtle, and the choſen veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of Chryſte, dyd ſoo muche eſteame the aucthoritie of hys aunciettes, with the whyche he deſyred to aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his faith &amp; preachinge, howe much more then ſhall it become vs igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and graceles, in compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon, to obeye and folowe the vniuerſall antiquitie of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke doctryne, an infallible ſygne of the catholike Church? And not to enclyne to a Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne neuer receyued nor prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed in Chryſt hys vniuerſall church, but in all ages, and in al countryes, profeſſing Chriſt, iuſtly condempned for hereſye. Therefore moſt plaine it is, the late Doctryne heare in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, not to be a ſounde, but a corrupte Doctryne, not catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:60"/> not vniuerſal, but party<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer and, pertiall, not ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, nor knowen, but ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unge to Chryſt his auncient ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke Church, the onely trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure houſe of GOD, and of the ryght wourſhyppyng of God. Here bicauſe I wold be loth to be tedious, I wyll ſurceaſe to ſpeake any more of antyquyty, and procede to the declaration of the thyrde ſygne, whych is vnytie.<note place="margin">Vnitie</note> Where is not conſent, vnytie, and agreament in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, there is ſciſme, diuiſion, and hereſye. Wherefore the catholyke Churche (whereof Chryſt is the hed) who is oure peace,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2</note> and hath made of bothe Iues, and gentyles, before dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded, in relygion, one bodye, is not a myſhapen, confuſed, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10406:60"/> diſordered multitude, but it is a conuocation, moſte ordrelye ſhapen, of moſte conſonant or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, and proportion, and that of beleauyng people, vnyted and lyncked togyther in one religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of our Sauyour Chryſte, by one fayth and his viſyble ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes,<note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Fauſt. lib <hi>9.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle Paule taught the Coryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans, broughte then by falſe teachers, into ſcyſme, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace vnytye, ſaying. <hi>Obſecro uos per nomen domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>ut id ipſum dicatis omnes, &amp; non ſint in nobis ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mata, ſitis autem perfecti in eodem ſenſu, et in eadem ſententia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I exhorte you in the name of our lorde Ieſus Chryſt, that ye all ſaye one thynge, and that there be no ſciſmes among you but be ye perfect in one ſence &amp; one mynde. The ſame vnytye
<pb facs="tcp:10406:61"/> Paule teacheth by the ſimily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a corporall body, which as it is compact of many mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers, in ſuch a harmonye, that ther is mutual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticipatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; mutual nur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditi &amp; helth among them, euen ſo the myſtycall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Sauyoure Ieſu, the Churche, is knytte together in one ſpyrytuall ſocyetye, wyth ſuche a vnytye, that there is a common and a mutuall parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, of the whole myſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body, the vniuerſal church in thoſe ſpyrytuall thynges, whyche be ſpyrytual nurriture of the ſoules, in chryſtian rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon, vnto the atchyuynge of lyfe eternall, ſcyſme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo contrary vnto the vnytye of Chryſtes Churche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule dyd wryte vnto the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynthyans,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:61"/> beyng in diuiſyon and contention, theſe wordes enſuyng.<note place="margin">1. Co. 11</note> 
               <hi>Si quis autem uidetur conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſus eſſe, nos talem conſuetudinem non habemus, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eccleſia dei.</hi> Yf any man do appeare to be contenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, he muſt knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no ſuche cuſtome, nether the church of God. Note here that contention concernyng faythe and chryſten life, is not among the catholykes, the vniuerſall congregation of God, accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to vnitie, and not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And therfore we reade in ſcrypture <hi>Deus qui inhabitare facit vnanimes in domo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 67.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is god whych maketh peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one mynd, to dwel in his houſe, whych is the Catholike Churche.</p>
            <p>Wherby it is moſt manyfeſte that ſcyſme, diuyſion and conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon
<pb facs="tcp:10406:62"/> be manyfeſt ſygnes of the vnleafull aſſembles of herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and vnity the moſt vndou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and manyfeſt token of the leafull and godly congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faythfulles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie plainlie to declare, the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures affyrme to be but one church as ye maye reade in the geneſis.<note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> We had but one arcke the expreſſe fygure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, therfore Chryſte hath but one churche, that the veryty maye aunſwer the figure. Alſo in the ſeconde booke of Moyſes it is written.<note place="margin">Cipri. de coena do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> 
               <hi>In vna domo commeditur agnus</hi> The lambe ſhalbe eaten in one houſe, the which houſe Saint Cypryan vnderſtandeth to be the churche, ſaying. <hi>Vna domus est eccleſie in qua agnus editur.</hi> There is one houſe of the churche in the
<pb facs="tcp:10406:62"/> whych the lambe is eaten. The lyke ſaying hath S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten addynge vnto Churche, this worde Cotholyke, which is thys. <hi>In una domo agnus comeditur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ſermo. de uigil. pen tec.</note> 
               <hi>quia in una eccleſia catholica uera hoſtia re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demptoris immolatur.</hi> The lambe is eaten in one houſe, bycauſe the true and very hoſte and obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our redemer, is offered in one catholyk Church. Thus Saynt Auſten teacheth to be but one churche, and the ſame to haue the tytle of Catholyke, whych ſygnifyeth vniuerſall, to the condempnation of the particular Churche, of ſcyſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tykes, and in the ſame one ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke Church not a figure of oure redeamer, but the verye true hoſte of our redemer, to be offred. The whiche catholyke
<pb facs="tcp:10406:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:64"/> Churche,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> Chryſte alſo calleth, <hi>Vnum ouile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12</note> One folde &amp; flocke, &amp; Paul both to the Romanes, &amp; alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epheſyans,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> affirmeth the multytude of faythfulles to be one body, and therefore S. Auſten agaynſt the Donatiſts ſayeth.<note place="margin">Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Donatiſt li. <hi>1.</hi> ca <hi>10</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vna eſt eccleſia, que ſola catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica nominatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The church is one which only is named catholicke, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof Chryſt becam the hedde coppelinge corner ſtone,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> wherupon and by whome the vniuerſall edyficer the vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall churche of bothe Iues and Gentyles, ſhoulde be buylded, brought, and reconſyled in to one body. To be brefe, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius a notable greeke wryter, hath wrytten of thys vnytye as foloweth. <hi>Eccleſia velut vnam
<pb facs="tcp:10406:64"/> habet animam et idem cor, et predicat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiphan. to. <hi>2.</hi> li. <hi>1.</hi> Iren. li. <hi>1,</hi> capi. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>docer et tradit, velut vno ore predita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Churche hath as it were one mynd and one hart, &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth, teacheth, &amp; giueth tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as it were endued wyth one mouth, as had the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue Church, by this teſtimony of Luke folowyng.<note place="margin">Actes. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Erat omnium qui credebant cor unum et anima vna.</hi> Of all whych did beleue, was one hart and one mynd. So much dyd Chryſte our head requyre vnytie in hys Churche, that he requyred it in two or three, and to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made moſt comfortable promyſe ſaying.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> Yf two of you doo agree vpon earthe of anye thyng, whatſoeuer they aſke, it ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be gyuen them of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whyche is in Heauen, as was vnto the three Chyldren,<note place="margin">Dani. 3.</note> agreyng in one fayth, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:10406:65"/> furnace. To commende amonge other godly thynges vnto vs thys moſte neceſſarye vnytie, our peace maker Ieſus Chryſt, ordeyned his very real body and bloude, in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which be of many reduced and brought to one, as in brede and wine, for of many graines is made one breade whych eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentlye proueth an indiuiſible ſocietye, &amp; an inſeparable vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be in and among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole vnyuerſall multytude of bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng people, ſpredde abroade in al the worlde, whych notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge theyr corporall dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, be broughte into one bodye by conſente of myndes, vnitie of faith, of Sacraments and of charytye, the bande of peace, as is manyfeſte by thys
<pb facs="tcp:10406:65"/> text of Paule, the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">1. Co. 10</note> 
               <hi>Vnus panis et unum corpus multi ſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We beinge many are one bred and one body for all we parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of one bread the bodye of Chryſte, do declare our ſelues (although many in nomber) to be one lofe of bread, compact of many graynes, that is to ſaye, to be one body of Chryſt, couni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of many members, hauing one fayth, one baptyſme &amp; one Lorde. And as al the members of Chryſt, are by one fayth and one maner of Sacramentes, made one body, ſo are they by the ſame, vnited to one hed our Ieſus Chryſte, of the whyche inſeparable vnitye, that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnyon and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſbande wyth the wyfe, is a greate Sacrament and a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li
<pb facs="tcp:10406:66"/> perfect ſigne, as this of Paul wytneſſeth <hi>Sacramentum hoc magnum est, ego autem dico in Chriſto et eccleſia.</hi> Thys is a greate ſacrament, but I ſpeake of Chryſte and of hys church, that is to ſaie, this ſacrament (meanynge matry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony) is a greate &amp; a worthy ſacrament not of nor in it ſelfe, but bycauſe it is by deuyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution a holye perfecte Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, and ſygne of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiſible vnyon and vnitye of Chriſt the hed with the church hys bodi. To be brefe, al Chriſt hys ſacramentes, myſteryes &amp; doctryne, do tende fully and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye to the auauncement of vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye and concorde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. to <hi>2</hi> epiſ. <hi>152.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Quiſquis ergo ab eccleſia catholica fuerit ſeperatus, quantumlibet laudabiliter ſe ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere existimet hoc ſolo ſcelere, quod a chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti unitate defunctus eſt, non habebit uitam
<pb facs="tcp:10406:66"/> ſed ira dei manet ſuper eum.</hi> Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer therefore ſhalbe ſeperated from thys catholyke Churche, albeit he thinke hym ſelfe to liue neuer ſoo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, yet for thys onelye myſchyfe, that he is ſeparated from the vnitie of Chryſt, he ſhal not haue lyfe, but the wrathe of God reſteth vpon hym.<note place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Thus you may eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dently vnderſtand vnitie to be a ſure token of the Catholyke Churche, from the which thoſe fragementes, that be dyuided and broken, doo publyſhe and thruſt fourth dyſſonante, pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt and contrariant Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, by the vyolente perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, and inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud ſpyryte of error. As nowe in our tyme, it is mooſte open to euery learned man, what a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious
<pb facs="tcp:10406:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:68"/> noumber, of contrary ſectes hath iſſued, yea braſt out of the puddle ſprynges, of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hereſies, as Corall Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Ecolampadia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Swin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glyans, Anabaptyſtans, Liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tines, yea Nouatians, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, with many other, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of euery one diſagreeth from another, and frome verytye it ſelf, conſenting againſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, agreyng almoſte in nothynge but againſt agrement, diuided in all thinges but in perſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the vnytye of Chryſt hys vnicall churche (as Pilate and Herode in nothynge accorded but onlye agaynſte our peace Chryſt hym ſelfe) beyng more vyolent,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.</note> then the Iues, whych wolde not deuyde Chryſt hys coate, wythout ſeame or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:68"/> ſygnyfyeng the vnytye of hys churche, ſaying. <hi>Non ſcindamus cam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.</note> Let vs not cutte or deuyde it. They are not therfore to be credyted, nor to be taken for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, nor for members ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, but to be fledde, eſchewed, abhorred, as ſedicious me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the dyſcorderable of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych ſyttynge in the chayre of peſtilence, doo with peſtyfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous doctryne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> corrupt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolue, ſoo muche as in them is, the quyete concord of Chryſte, hys miſtical body, the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall church, and do reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the as Iannes and Mambres reſyſted Moyſes. Thus we knowynge what the Churche is, where it is, and that it is ſenſible, vyſible, and manifeſt,<note place="margin">2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the infallyble tokens, as
<pb facs="tcp:10406:69"/> vnyuerſality antiquitie, &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye thereof, whereby it is dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from the Churche ſcyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matycall, we cannot without extreame iniury of our hed Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt, and the holy Ghoſt contynually reſydent therein, forſake the holy vnitye, vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalytye, and antiquitye of hys holy Catholyke churche, to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the newelye publyſhed &amp; the late crept in prophane fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy, diuiſed in the deuyded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uentycles, of heretycall ſcyſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tykes, conſpiryng agaynſt the whole aunciet church, for who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer forſaketh that olde au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci vniuerſal church, only conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in one true doctrine, they forſake Chryſt hymſelf, the hed thereof, and the ſpyryte of God abydynge therein.</p>
            <p>We cannot forſake the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:10406:69"/> but we muſt nedes forſake the hed Ieſus Chriſt who is truth we cannot depart from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of god the church, but we muſt nedes depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god dweling in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame houſe And as god is vnitie, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of vnitie, ſo hath he vnited to him one ſpouſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike church of vnite, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of euery faythfull ſeuerally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted is a chyld, and as he is but one hed, ſo hathe he but one myſtycal body the church, vnited, to hym, by one faythe, and one baptyſme, of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che body euery Chryſtian reke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ſingulerly a part is a mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber. As he is nother a partyall nor a partyculer God, of thys or that country, but God of all realmes, Empyres, and naty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Likewiſe his onely ſpouſe and bodye, the Churche, is not
<pb facs="tcp:10406:70"/> a pertyculer multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in thys or that nacyon one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſall chriſtian multitude in al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, realms &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, through out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world. As god is not a you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or a newe god, lately ſprong vp, lykewyſe hys ſayde ſpouſe &amp; miſtical body, is not yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g newe and late, but of olde antyquyty euen from the beginnynge.</p>
            <p>Wherefore you can in no caſe excuſe your ſelfes at the drede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of Iudgement, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may well dyſcerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new and late ſpronge vp ſcyſmaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call churches, diſſentyng from the vniuerſall aunciette co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the vniuerſall aunciett con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Chryſtes faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles, agreyng conſtantlye in one faith &amp; in one true religion from Chryſtes time continual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:10406:70"/> and perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to this day and ſoo wyll contynue to the worldes ende.</p>
            <p>So that it is in you, whether that you wyll beleue that late vpſtarted anguler and perty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer Churche of contentious deſſention, whereof lying Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than is the hed, or the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall aunciett church of vnytye, the hed wherof is Chryſt, who is verytie. Whoſoeuer wilbe, partaker of the lyuely ſucke, &amp; ſappe, deſcendyng from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hed Ieſus Chryſte, into hys onely body the catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, and into euerye ſynguler, member thereof.</p>
            <p>Let him not diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre him ſelfe from that lyuely body by anye kinde of newe doctrine, dyſtre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pant from the olde auntiette &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10406:71"/> vnyuerſall doctryne receaued from Chryſt and his primatiue churche, for he that diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth hym ſelfe from the church, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth himſelfe from chriſt the hed thereof <hi>Non tenens ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut, ex quo totum corpus per nexus et coniunc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiones ſubminiſtratum et constructum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collo. 2. Ephe. 4.</note> 
               <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit in augmentum dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not hauyng nor holdyng the hed, of whom the whole bodi by ioyntes and ioyninges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauyng nurriture and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact in one, groweth to a godly per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection, the whole body is the whole vniuerſall Churche, the hed is Chryſt, who is lyfe, and the ioyntes wherwith the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ioyned to the hed,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> be faith charitie and the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, by whome ſpyrituall nurryſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and lyfe, be deriued into
<pb facs="tcp:10406:71"/> the ſaid vniuerſal body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church and to euery member thereof, ſo that conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, he that diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeperateth him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, ſeperateth hym ſelfe from lyfe, let vs not therfore forſake the vnytye of Chryſt hys churche, for that holi martyr and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent clarke. S Cipryan ſayeth alſo. <hi>Hanc vnitatem qui non tenet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cipri. de ſimp. pre</note> 
               <hi>dei legem non tenet, non tenet patris et filij fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, vitam non tenet, et ſalutem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that kepethe not thys vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, kepeth not the fayth of our father, and of hys ſone, he hath not lyfe and ſaluation, and to thend that we ſhould kepe this vnytye peace and concord, we are called into one bodye the Churche, as writeth Paule to the Colloſſyans.<note place="margin">Collo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In whoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lap the vniuerſal aunciett co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; the ſea Apoſtolyke, kepte
<pb facs="tcp:10406:72"/> that aunciette father, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable clerke, S. Auſten as is uydent by this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng.<note place="margin">Aug. to <hi>6</hi> in epi. ma ca. <hi>4.</hi> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uocant fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>damenti.</note> 
               <hi>Multa ſunt, quae me in eccleſie gremio iuſtiſſime tenent, tenet me conſenſio popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tenet authoritas, miraculis, inchoata, ſpeuutrita, charitate aucta, ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſtate firmata, tenet ab ipſa ſede petri A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postoli, cui paſcendas o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, ſuas post reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionem ſuam dominus, commendaui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad preſentem epiſcopatum, ſucceſſio ſacerdotum, tenet postremo ipſum catholice nomen quod non ſine cauſa interiam multas hereſes, ſola obtinuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many thynges ſaythe Auſten there be, whych do kepe me in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lappe of the catholike church The conſent of the people and nations kepeth me, the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie therof begonne by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, nowriſhed by hope, encre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſed by charytye, confyrmed &amp; eſtabliſhed by antiquitie ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:72"/>
            <p>The ſucceſſyon of pryſtes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeate of Peter thappoſtle, vnto whome our Lorde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted after his reſurrection, his ſhepe to be fedde, vnto this preſent Byſhoprycke, laſt of all kepeth me the churches name of catholyke, bycauſe not with out matter, amonge ſo manye hereſyes, ſhe onely hath had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyctory. This obedient chylde of our holy mother the church, Saint Auſten, declareth four pryncypall poyntes, which did holde hym in obedience vnto her, whych be theſe, conſent of al chryſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nations in one faith the antiquitie of the churches aucthoritie, and the vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the ſame, ſygnifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Catholyke, yea and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthoritie of the ſea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke
<pb facs="tcp:10406:73"/> of Peter, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedethe the ſucceſſyon of prye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes in the Church, of Chryſte, agaynſte the whyche ſea, Hel gates hath not preuayled, but from Peters tyme to thys day hath contynued the nexte hed vndre Chryſt of the catholyke churche, and hath ſtand in the fayth thereof, and ſo ſhall perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer to the worldes ende. And yet agaynſt al other the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſeas, hel force hath ſo auai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, that it hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubuerted, Foraſmuch as theſe fore poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes dyd kepe Saynt Auſten, in humble obedience vnto the Churche, out of the whyche is no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what ſhal al good chryſtyans recken one ſuche, whom the fame nothynge doo moue, ſurelye that they haue
<pb facs="tcp:10406:73"/> Chryſt and his Church in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and that the ſpyryte of truthe reſydente in the church is with them of no credence, &amp; yet they know the Church, for that, that the ſpyryte of verity is contynuallye reſyaunt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to be called in ſcrypture the houſe and temple of God, as for examyle <hi>An ueſcitis quod templum dei eſtis, et ſpiritus dei habitat in uobis?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Do not you knowe ſaythe Paule, that you be the temple of God, and that the holy goſt, doth dwell in you?</p>
            <p>Wherevppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that olde aunty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and excelent clarke Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,<note place="margin">Lacta. de uera ſap. li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>30</hi>
               </note> groundyng hymſelfe dyd wryght thys folowynge <hi>Sola igitur catholica eccleſia eſt, quae uerum cultum retinet, hic eſt fons veritatis, hoc eſt domicilium fidei, hoc templum dei, quo ſi quis non intrauerit, uel a quo ſi quis exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit
<pb facs="tcp:10406:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10406:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10406:75"/> aſpe uitae ac ſalutis eterne alienus eſt</hi> It is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely catholike church whych hath in it the true wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppinge of god, thys is the fountayne of truth, this is the manſyon houſe of faythe, thys is the temple of God, wherein yf any do not entre, or oute of whom yf any do depart, he is a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; far diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope of lyfe, and ſaluation eternall. Wherewyth accordethe, that holy learned Byſſhoppe &amp; S. Epiphanius ſaying. <hi>Eſt uia regia, ſancta dei eccleſia et iter ueritatis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph.</hi> 10 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2,</note>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Churche of God, is the Heauenlye Kynges hyghe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>way, and the path of truthe. Wherefore ſeyng that ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and truth be onely in chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes catholyke and vniuerſall churche, and not in particuler
<pb facs="tcp:10406:75"/> conuenticles, let vs in all kynd of ſcyſmes, diuiſions, factions, ſectes, ehreſyes, and erroures, cleaue ſticke, and ſtande, with conſtant obedience to the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable iudgement, determyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke Churche. For ſeynge that Chryſt is in the myddes of .ii. or .iii. gathered together in his name, it muſte nedes followe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is in his own body the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, the whole ſocyetye &amp; vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall congregation, of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leauynge people, lyncked and gathered together, by conſent in his name, and vnited to him as the body to the hedde.</p>
            <p>Than cannot we but graunte that the church of Chryſt muſt nedes be the true interpreteſſe of holy ſcrypture, and truly to
<pb facs="tcp:10406:76"/> decide and determyne the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſies which mani do ſtir vp after euery of there pryuate immaginations, for as Saint Auſten accurſeth hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other beleaueth to haue aucthorytye or hath in reuerente any ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Aug, ſer, <hi>129</hi>
               </note> beſides thoſe ſcryptures which the catholycke churche hath receaued.</p>
            <p>Lykewyſe vndoutedly he cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch, as make or do beleue or reuerenceth any interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, made of the ſcryptures, agaynſte and contrarye to the Churches interpretations, for beynge not leafull to receaue Scryptures vnproued by the catholyke Churche, it is not leafull to receiue ſtraung inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretations thereof, and not ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proued by the ſame Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyderyng,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:76"/> that in the Churche onely, is the truth, as wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that olde author Ireneus wrytyng theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vbi eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſia, ibi ſpiritus, et ubi ſpiritus dei, illic eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſia et omnis gratia, ſpiritus autem ueritas.</hi> Where the Church is, there is the ſpyryte of God, and where the ſpyrit of Godis, there is the Churche and all grace. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyryte truely is trouth, which moſte playnelye agreeth with the Doctryne of Paule.<note place="margin">1. Tim 3 Pſal. 88.</note> 
               <hi>Domus dei eſt eccleſia dei uiui, colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na et firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ueritatis.</hi> The houſe of god, is the Churche of God, the pyller &amp; the fyrme vpholdyng of truth. And therefore the ſayd Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us wryteth alſo thus.<note place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>5</hi> pag. <hi>319.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiae pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicatio uera et firma eſt, apud quam una et eadem ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lutis uia in uniuerſo mundo oſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditur.</hi> The preachyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is true, firme, and ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, in
<pb facs="tcp:10406:77"/> whome is one verye waye of ſaluation, ſhewed and many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt through the whole worlde For euery where ſayeth he the Churche preacheth the truthe, Lykewyſe Orygen taughte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> onely to be the beleaued truth,<note place="margin">Orige. in prodemio petiarcho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> whych in nothyng dyſagreeth from the churches tradytion, and therefore Sainte Auſten, dyd wryte as foloweth.<note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra epiſt. Man. ca <hi>5</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ego ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro non crederem euangelo niſime catholice eccleſiae commoueret authoritas</hi> I wold not beleaue the Goſpell yf the authoritie of the Churche dyd not moue me thereto for if the Churche had not approued &amp; wytneſſed the truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, we ſhoulde haue bene no leſſe vncertayne of it then we are of the Goſpelles aſcrybed, to Thomas Bartylmue and
<pb facs="tcp:10406:77"/> Nychodeme, ye maye further reade in Chriſoſtome.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. tom, <hi>2.</hi> in Manh. <hi>10.</hi> mundo.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia habet veres oculos, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idelicet eccleſiaſticos at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> doctores, qui vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſcripturis miſteria dei, de quibus dicuntur videntes.</hi> The churche hath true eyes, that is to ſaye preachers and teachers whych doo ſe the myſteryes of god Wherefor theye are called <hi>Videntes,</hi> that is to ſaye ſeynge, perceyuynge, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the ſayde myſterye, To be bryfe Saynt Hilary, calleth the church the mouth of Chriſt ſaying. <hi>Os christi eccleſiam eſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hilari. in pſal. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>et prophetica &amp; apoſtolica aucthoritas eſt.</hi> The prophetycall and the apoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolycall aucthorytye is, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church is the mowthe of chriſt The ſame affyrmythe Auſten ſaying.<note place="margin">Au. in Io. <hi>15.</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>88</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Christus per eccleſiam ſuam loquitur gentibus.</hi> Chryſt ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:10406:78"/> to the gentyles, and people by hys churche, for Chryſte ſayde <hi>Non uos estis qui loquimini,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ſpiritus pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tris uestri qui loquitur in uobis.</hi> It is not you which do ſpeake but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiryte of truth which ſpeketh in you,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.</note> he therfore that heareth you my mowthe, heareth me. Wherfore in all controuerſyes and dowtes aryſynge or wreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted out of written ſcriptures, which can nether heare, iudge, nor ſpeke the wyll and pleſure of god therin conteyned.</p>
            <p>We muſte nedes take for oure refuge and perfect inſtruction the lyuely temple of God, the lyuely orgayne, and inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the holy Ghoſt the churche, lyuely and fully repreſented by the general counſailes, as this realme is fully repreſented by
<pb facs="tcp:10406:78"/> the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, bycauſe all and euery member of the Churche nor all and euerye member of thys realme, cannot be aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled conueniently together in one place, the whych generall counceles aucthoritie. is moſt holſome &amp; ſounde, as teacheth Saynt Auſten. In ſo doynge, we ſhall follow the example of the good chryſtians of Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och, whiche when Paule and Barnabye were moleſted and troubled with the great diſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and ſeditious diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of their aduerſaries the Iues, did ſend vnto the Apoſtles and pryſtes in Ieruſalem, for the diſcuſſion of the queſtion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vpon accordyng to the olde lawe commaundinge the Iues in all diffycyll and dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:10406:79"/> mattyres to aſcende vnto the pryſtes, and not to the law it ſelfe, and of them to requyre the truth and the mynd of the lawe,<note place="margin">Agge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they ſhuld declyne to no ſyde, for the lawe is to be requyred as affirmeth the prophet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſtes mouth.<note place="margin">Mala. 2,</note> To the whych chryſtyan bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles and preſtes gathered to gether in one, dyd wryght.<note place="margin">Actes. 16</note> 
               <hi>Viſum est ſpiritui ſancto &amp; nobis</hi> It pleaſeth the holy ghoſt and vs. They ſayde not it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth the holye ghoſte and ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is but a dead do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be and a not ſpeakyng letter, but it pleaſeth the holy ghoſt &amp; vs, vs the temple of oure lyuynge God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> the Epiſtle and ſcripture of Chryſte, wrytten, not wyth yncke, but with the ſpirite, of
<pb facs="tcp:10406:79"/> our lyuyng God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> not in ſtonye tables, or in other outewarde ſubſtaunce, but in the fleſhye tables, and inward ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mans harte, wherefore dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>btes moued out of Scripture, are not to be determined bi the deade lettre written w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yncke, but by the liuely ſcripture writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt in faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full mennes hartes, for ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wrytten with yncke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe it conteyneth Godds moſt vndouted truthe, yet by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it heareth not, ſpeakethe not, compareth not, nor ponde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the matters incontrouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye, it cannotte iudge, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence of the truthe. The holy counſell thereof aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled at Iheruſalem, ſayd it ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth the holy ghoſt and vs, the
<pb facs="tcp:10406:80"/> lyuely ſcrypture of Chryſt, the ſpeakyng mouthe and lyuelye inſtrument of the holy ghoſte, Whoſe determination,<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> whan the bretherne had readde they ioyed in the comforte receiued theirin, wherefore let vs relyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſhe the diſſentions, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentions proceadynge oute of priuate preſumptuous braines and humbly obeye and ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye receyue the deciſions and determinations of Chryſtes ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke churche, whome the ſpyryte of verytye teacheth to ſpeake all the truth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 16.</note> Let vs (I ſaye) follow the counſell of S. Auſten <hi>Diuinam ueritatem in una eccleſiateneamus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra cona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ. post cellat ca. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>et humanas, lites aliquando fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niamus</hi> Let vs kepe ſayth Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Godds truth whych is in the church of vnitie, and ſo lett vs
<pb facs="tcp:10406:80"/> once fynyſhe humayne conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Non enim diſſenſionis eſt deus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14</note> 
               <hi>ſed pacis.</hi> For god is not the god of diſſenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the God of peace. To whoſe mouthe. which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnyuerſall catholycke church,<note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> and to the doctryne proceding out therof, as obedient ſhepe of his flocke, we are moſt bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and obeye accordyng to thys of Chryſt, my ſhepe do here my voyſe, doo beleue mye wordes, and do folowe me, ſoo that hys Diſciples doo heare, beleue, and followe him, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in his choſen and lyuelye mouth the churche, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfolde wyſedome of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.</note> is made open and knowen by his Churche, as affyrmyth Paule. Wherefore the Churche being his owne mouth, muſte nedes
<pb facs="tcp:10406:81"/> expounde, interpretate &amp; open hys owne Scrptures, mooſte agreable to his owne mynde, and ſynce that in the mouthe of two or three wytneſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſteth euerye matter,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> then the Teſtimonye of the mouthe of Chryſt the vniuerſall churche, muſt neds &amp; of neceſſitie ſtand.</p>
            <p>And hys churches true eyes, as preachers and teachers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the churche, the mouthe of Chryſte, doth truly ſee, and perceue the miſteries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. Let vs leaue therefore our arrogante preſumptions, the mother of all hereſy in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng of the holy worde of god,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>co.</hi> 3.</note> the whiche God reſyſteth and let vs wyth meke humilitie,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Petre.</hi> 5</note> to whome god giueth grace, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte our priuate fallible iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:81"/> to the infallyble aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciet Conſent of the whole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Catholyke Churche. whych w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one harte and mynd beleuethe, wyth perfecte eyes ſeeth, &amp; wyth one mouthe prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth one truthe, as affyrmith the ancthorytyes before reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, let (vs I ſay) duryng this our Pilgremage in the deſert of this worlde, walke in the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke churche, the heauenly kynges hygh way, the way of truth, the which truthe they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be out of the church,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> be alwaye ſekynge and neuer fyndynge that we may in the end of this our ſayd iorneye heare in the Mylytant Church, acheue vp to the Churche aboue tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</p>
            <p>Where we maye in truth,
<pb facs="tcp:10406:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnytye and peace honor wyth one harte,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> one mynde, one mouth, our euer lyuing god of peace, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternal, be al praiſe honor, &amp; glori eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nallye. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Londo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Paules Churchyard, at the ſigne of the holy Ghoſt, by Ihon Cawod, Printer to the Kyng and Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10406:82"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
